<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Angliæ speculum: or Englands looking-glasse. Devided into two pats [sic], / by C.VV. Mercer.</title>
            <title>Angliæ speculum. Parts 1 and 2</title>
            <author>Mercer, William, 1605?-1676?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E327_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200657</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861339</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861339</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113472</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113472)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E327[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Angliæ speculum: or Englands looking-glasse. Devided into two pats [sic], / by C.VV. Mercer.</title>
                  <title>Angliæ speculum. Parts 1 and 2</title>
                  <author>Mercer, William, 1605?-1676?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho: Paine.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In two parts. "Angliæ speculum: .. The second part" has separate dated title page; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L M⁶ N-P⁴ Q² .</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 9th 1645"; the I in imprint date crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Angliae Speculum: OR ENGLANDS LOOKING-GLASSE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Devided into two pats,</hi> By C. VV. MERCER.</p>
                  <q>Scribimus indocti, doctique poaemata paſsim.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Paine.</hi> MDCXLVI.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:2"/>
                  <head>ANGLIAE SPECVLVM. <hi>Or ENGLANDS LOOKING-GLASSE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <l>You may perceive, and in this Looking-glaſſe</l>
                  <l>ſee Englands worth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s, either more or leſſe:</l>
                  <l>And in the ſame, look, and you likewiſe ſhall</l>
                  <l>ſee, in the face, Lord <hi>ESSEX,</hi> Generall.</l>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of a mirror</figDesc>
                        <head>ENGLAND</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="frontispiece_and_dedication">
                  <div type="apology_for_frontispiece">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:3"/>
                     <l>The Authors picture uſually is put,</l>
                     <l>and not the Patrons, this they tell me, but,</l>
                     <l>I pray, who cares to ſee a peece ſo bad</l>
                     <l>as I? but I have ſeen them running mad</l>
                     <l>To ſee my Lord, but here now they may ſtand</l>
                     <l>and hear and ſee, and have him in their hand:</l>
                     <l>Beſides, another of my reaſons are</l>
                     <l>his Excellence ought to be ſingular.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="apology_for_dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:3"/>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Vpon the Dedication of my Booke.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> Did intend, but now I come too late,</l>
                     <l>it was the Printers fault, who did not get</l>
                     <l>My Glaſſe in time, for this was all my drift,</l>
                     <l>to give my <hi>Lord</hi> this, for a new-years gift:</l>
                     <l>But it is never out of time to take;</l>
                     <l>this I created for your Lordſhips ſake.</l>
                     <l>And gives you here, what beſt I may, and can,</l>
                     <l>My humbleſt ſervice, whilſt I am a man.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </lg>
                  <div type="dedication">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:4"/>
                     <p>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MOST VALIANT AND THRICE worthily Renowned LORD, ROBERT Earle of ESSEX, and EVVE, &amp;c. His EXCELLENCIE, <hi>My moſt Noble Lord and Patron.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The continuance of all chief Honors, and true Happines in higheſt meaſure, in this life, and the fruition of all felicity in the Life to come,</hi> Is VViſhed, By the moſt humbleſt, and unworthyeſt, of all your Excellencies Servitours, <hi>William Mercer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I'm reall, rec'iv' me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I give my ſelf herewith, I'm reall, rec'iv' me,</l>
                        <l>if I were ten times better, ye might have me,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="frontispiece">
                     <p>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:4"/>
                        <figure>
                           <figDesc>portrait of Robert Devereux Earl of Essex</figDesc>
                           <head>ROBERTUS ILLUSTRISSIMUS &amp; EXCELLENTISSIMUS HAEROS COMES ESSEXIAE PROQ TUTAMINE CŌITIORM ANGLIAE NUPERRIME DUX SUPREMUS</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>I once resolu'd that nothing should be ſeen,</l>
                              <l>And so presum'd to interpose, a Screen.</l>
                              <l>Becaus I thought the Multitude with greed,</l>
                              <l>Would love to looke upon the <hi>Peece,</hi> not read.</l>
                              <l>But in the end, determind for to take,</l>
                              <l>Aſide the Curtaine, for the <hi>Figur's</hi> sake.</l>
                              <l>That ſeeing first, this <hi>Haero's</hi> in the face,</l>
                              <l>They then might read, but in the ſecond place,</l>
                              <l>Englands brave <hi>Gen'rall,</hi> in its just defence,</l>
                              <l>Yet but the Shaddows of his <hi>EXCELLENCE.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </lg>
                           <byline>W. Marſhall ſculpsit.</byline>
                        </figure>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagrams">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:5"/>
                     <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, THE EARLE OF <hi>ESSEX,</hi> HIS EXCELLENCY:</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr. 1.</head>
                        <l>Earl Robert Deavorex's Anagr.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A real dexterous Orbe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>A real dexterous Orbe, ſo fix'd, agreeing,</l>
                        <l>by whom we liv'd, we mov'd, and had our being.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Earle Robert Deavorex. Anagr. 2.</head>
                        <l>Our rare exalter robd,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>Our rare exalter robd, brave Eſſex, hee</l>
                        <l>Is robd from us, ſo we muſt ruin'd be.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Robert Deavorex, Anagr. 3.</head>
                        <l>Brave Or'tor ex'eed,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>Brave Or'tor exceed, why? ſay exceed,</l>
                        <l>Your Excellence ſurpaſſe them all, indeed.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Robert Deavorex. Anagr. 4.</head>
                        <l>Vexe art, or Robd,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>Vexe art, or Robd, forloe envious men,</l>
                        <l>Vſe art to rob thee, vex and rob them then.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="acrostic_sonnet">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:5"/>
                     <head>Sonnet Acroſtick.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <hi>R</hi>are</hi> and renown'd <hi>exalter</hi> of our Faith,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>f all <hi>our</hi> hopes, <hi>robd,</hi> as it were by death,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>B</hi>elov'd, above expreſſions of my pen,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ſteem'd by Angels, as much as by men,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>R</hi>enown'd for ever, for thy feits in warre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>T</hi>he times to come ſhall us exceed as farre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>D</hi>ay after day, to ſing thy praiſes then,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ven as we now, diſtinguiſh thee from men:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>V</hi>nto thoſe Trophees, which we take in hand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi>r to thoſe Bayes, which on thy Temples ſtand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>R</hi>eturn we will, and on theſe princely browes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>E</hi>ven place thoſe Trophies, and thoſe Bayes with vowes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>X</hi>ceeding joyfull, and ſurpaſſing all, to eternize our Noble Generall.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:6"/>
                     <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, MY moſt Noble Lord Generall his Excellency, and my moſt honourable Patron.</head>
                     <l>BEhold I come, and humbly on my knee,</l>
                     <l>preſent my ſelf in thankfulneſſe, to thee.</l>
                     <l>Renowned Champion, choſen firſt in chief,</l>
                     <l>For Parliament, and Proteſtants relief:</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee</hi> brave <hi>Eſſex,</hi> ſingular, and ſuch,</l>
                     <l>Who never can be magnified too much:</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> who when fair Englands worthies went,</l>
                     <l>And weigh'd thy worth, by votes in Parliament,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>thee</hi> compar'd with all thoſe prudent men,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe vertues were laid to the touchſtone then,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> I ſay, who was ſo well belov'd,</l>
                     <l>The reſolutions could not be remov'd,</l>
                     <l>Of neither noble, nor the mean degree:</l>
                     <l>But all did ſmile, and condiſcend to <hi>thee:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> even <hi>thee,</hi> who if I dare proteſt,</l>
                     <l>Did then accept, when no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n thought it beſt</l>
                     <l>To be beginner, nor to put his hand</l>
                     <l>To contradict his Soveraigns command,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee</hi> whoſe courage, by conſent, I ſay,</l>
                     <l>Was found the fitteſt to command the day:</l>
                     <l>And ſtill to <hi>thee,</hi> who with a loyall heart,</l>
                     <l>Did far remove all private thoughts apart:</l>
                     <l>And whoſe impartiall prudence, did by far</l>
                     <l>Exceed the uſuall ſtratagems of warre:</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> who ventur'd when the Royall power,</l>
                     <l>Appear'd in perſon, and proclaim'd the houre,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:6"/>Wherein he would, with his triumphing band,</l>
                     <l>(As he did term them) all his foes withſtand;</l>
                     <l>Did ſound his Trumps, and cauſed beat the drum,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe noiſe did ſeem to ſay O! dare ye come?</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> I ſay, who then with courage great,</l>
                     <l>Did Eccho back thoſe voyces with delight,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid, O come, let us defend our faith,</l>
                     <l>We ſhall prevail, aſtoniſh not at death:</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> I ſay, ſo pregnant, I approach,</l>
                     <l>And all thy actions, worthily avouch,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee,</hi> I owe, and really will pay,</l>
                     <l>Even what I am, what I can do, or ſay,</l>
                     <l>Thy far fetched vertues are above my wing,</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſoar to ſuch a ſacred thing,</l>
                     <l>Yet to my power, I muſt preſent as much</l>
                     <l>As is, and hopes, thou wilt accept of ſuch,</l>
                     <l>I was a witnes, of the weaker kind,</l>
                     <l>To thy undaunted and magnifique mind:</l>
                     <l>And had the honour for to have command,</l>
                     <l>By thy Commiſſion, Signed with thy hand:</l>
                     <l>Was one who firſt, was entered in the time</l>
                     <l>When ſouldiers ſins were reckoned for a crime,</l>
                     <l>And ever ſince, continued ſtill, for one,</l>
                     <l>Till thou laid down thy high Commiſſion:</l>
                     <l>O! at the firſt, when no man would ingage,</l>
                     <l>Nor go to act upon that Tragick ſtage:</l>
                     <l>Nor undertake to meddle with the thing</l>
                     <l>So thought, for to reflect upon the King:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>thou,</hi> whoſe faith and courage did exceed</l>
                     <l>The ſubtle number, ſaw the preſent need:</l>
                     <l>For to oppoſe thoſe errors then begun,</l>
                     <l>And did apply thee to it, did not ſhun</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:7"/>The ſentence which thy ſoveraigne did expreſſe,</l>
                     <l>Knowing thou meant his lawes not to tranſgreſſe:</l>
                     <l>But when all others of the higher ſort,</l>
                     <l>For ſuch a charge, confeſt they all came ſhort:</l>
                     <l>Or if they knew that they could manage it,</l>
                     <l>There was ſome ſecret, which they thought not fit:</l>
                     <l>Therefore forbore, but ſtanders by did ſee,</l>
                     <l>They all determin'd, <hi>thou</hi> wert onely he</l>
                     <l>Who could, and muſt, or if thou wouldſt not do it,</l>
                     <l>All muſt be quiet, no man will go to it.</l>
                     <l>Some did deſire it in their hearts, but that</l>
                     <l>Was all the thing in ſecret aimed at,</l>
                     <l>They fain would riſe to have commanded all,</l>
                     <l>But durſt not run the hazard of a fall:</l>
                     <l>Here was the fault, they had ſome private aim:</l>
                     <l>Therefore I ceaſe, and ſay no more of them.</l>
                     <l>But Noble <hi>Eſſex</hi> thou wert all in all,</l>
                     <l>And muſt be choſen Englands Generall:</l>
                     <l>Thou hadſt no thought of Soveraignity,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſearcht in things conceived privately:</l>
                     <l>But undertook it for the Kingdoms good,</l>
                     <l>And for <hi>thy</hi> Princes priviledges ſtood:</l>
                     <l>No private aims importun'd <hi>thee,</hi> but ſtill</l>
                     <l>The publicks profit was <hi>thy</hi> practice, till</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thou</hi> hadſt trod down the number moſt of thoſe,</l>
                     <l>Who did preſume to be imployd as foes:</l>
                     <l>O! how thy ſpirit did appear abroad,</l>
                     <l>As onely <hi>thou</hi> eſtablisht were by God,</l>
                     <l>And how <hi>thy</hi> courage in the eyes of all,</l>
                     <l>Did make the armies cry aloud, and call,</l>
                     <l>Go on, go on, brave <hi>Eſſex</hi> is our guide:</l>
                     <l>Behold, his preſence makes us to confide:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:7"/>
                        <hi>Thou</hi> didſt appear, like <hi>Phaebus</hi> in his ſphaere,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy</hi> Armies as the ſtarres into the aire,</l>
                     <l>The boundleſſe Ocean of thy noble veines,</l>
                     <l>Gave influence to many thouſand ſtraines:</l>
                     <l>Nor didſt <hi>thou</hi> ſo diminiſh yet <hi>thy</hi> ſtore,</l>
                     <l>The more <hi>thou</hi> furniſhd, ſtill <hi>thy</hi> ſtock was more:</l>
                     <l>And as it prov'd, the ſpirits even of thoſe</l>
                     <l>Appeard much ſharper then the preſent foes</l>
                     <l>We now purſue; but policies in war</l>
                     <l>May oft prevail, and give advantage far:</l>
                     <l>Their former courage makes me more and more</l>
                     <l>Think, that they are not what they were before:</l>
                     <l>But now I muſt impart one paſſage yet,</l>
                     <l>I cannot chooſe, but muſt remember it:</l>
                     <l>Like as the Sun ſends out his beams of light,</l>
                     <l>But all of them returns to him at night:</l>
                     <l>So likewiſe thoſe who had their power of thee,</l>
                     <l>When thou forbore, no more abroad would be:</l>
                     <l>Who having done thy part abroad, thought ſit</l>
                     <l>For to afford thy preſence, and to ſit</l>
                     <l>In that aſſembly of the higheſt ſtrain,</l>
                     <l>From whence thou cam'ſt, and where thou art again.</l>
                     <l>To <hi>thee</hi> I come, imploring thou wilt be</l>
                     <l>My noble Patron, for to ſhelter me,</l>
                     <l>Which if thou wilt, ther's none I will avouch,</l>
                     <l>That for thy Names ſake, dare preſume to touch</l>
                     <l>Thoſe enterpriſes, humbly I preſent</l>
                     <l>Vnto my Lord, without a Complement.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_courteous_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:8"/>
                  <head>To the Curteous Reader.</head>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou ſees I ſtand reſolved to defend</l>
                  <l>What ever curſed malice dare pretend:</l>
                  <l>But cannot ſtil be preſent when they vent</l>
                  <l>And ſpit the venom of their diſcontent:</l>
                  <l>Therefore in abſence muſt appeal to thee,</l>
                  <l>For to aſsiſt if any injures me.</l>
                  <l>It is a thing ſo common to deride,</l>
                  <l>And throw a book diſdainfully aſide,</l>
                  <l>Or if they fortune for to ſee a name,</l>
                  <l>And hate the author, thats enough for them</l>
                  <l>They take no notice though the thing be juſt,</l>
                  <l>Miſlikes the bearer, therefore cannot truſt,</l>
                  <l>But more allowance I preſume to take,</l>
                  <l>They will beleeve me for my matters ſake:</l>
                  <l>Nor do I ſtrive to elevate my words,</l>
                  <l>Nor counterfet, but what the truth affords,</l>
                  <l>Nor have Is kill, nor knowledge for to skan,</l>
                  <l>Nor dare I flatter ſuch a faithfull man,</l>
                  <l>Nor have I practice for to put in verſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor wit enough his vertues to rehearſe,</l>
                  <l>As for my learning, to my ſhame I ſpeak it,</l>
                  <l>I may begin, and go to ſchool to ſeek it:</l>
                  <l>And dare proteſt for each year of my age,</l>
                  <l>I never read of verſes not a page:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:8"/>And Poets, whence I challenge no diſcent,</l>
                  <l>Though ſcarce of matter, meerly they invent,</l>
                  <l>But I a ſtranger to that ſtock, which ſprung</l>
                  <l>From out <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> and my muſe ſo young,</l>
                  <l>She never ſuckt the ſiſters ſacred font,</l>
                  <l>Nor d d repair the place where they were wont</l>
                  <l>To walk upon, to imitate thoſe nine:</l>
                  <l>Such is this ill bred baſtard muſe of mine:</l>
                  <l>She knowes of nothing, but uſurps the name,</l>
                  <l>Preſumes to ryme, ſince reckoned one of them;</l>
                  <l>Yet both of us you ſee are ſo well bred,</l>
                  <l>That we have written more then we have read</l>
                  <l>But famous poets furniſht with thoſe parts,</l>
                  <l>Of Natures gifts, and garniſht with the arts</l>
                  <l>Of learning fully, they can ſo indite,</l>
                  <l>As if it all were reall, that they write:</l>
                  <l>They can bring fictions far above the sky,</l>
                  <l>And forge inventions, but ſo cannot I:</l>
                  <l>I tell of nothing but what you have ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Nor prophecy, but tell you what hath been:</l>
                  <l>And heres my comfort, I have ſuch a theame</l>
                  <l>In entermedling with this Noble Name,</l>
                  <l>That not a man will murmure if he ſee</l>
                  <l>Me do my beſt, although in ſmall degree,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they know I cannot well eclips</l>
                  <l>Thoſe high conceptions entered in the lips</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:9"/>Of all that lives, exceeding ſo his ſex,</l>
                  <l>And in the Name of <hi>E. S. S. E. X.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That let me labour either more or leſſe,</l>
                  <l>This very name all nobleneſſe expreſſe:</l>
                  <l>Therefore 'tis folly for to crave thy aid</l>
                  <l>To pay this debt, which never can be paid:</l>
                  <l>For let me ſpeak, and all my ſpirits ſpend,</l>
                  <l>And ever write, and never make an end:</l>
                  <l>Yet in that boundleſse Ocean of his worth</l>
                  <l>I may well enter, cannot ſet it forth,</l>
                  <l>And ſeeking for to ſatisfie my mind,</l>
                  <l>I well may wander, but I cannot find</l>
                  <l>The thing I ſeek, and therefore will forbeare,</l>
                  <l>Can go no further, I muſt reſt me here.</l>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>W. M.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_critical_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:9"/>
                  <head>To the Criticall Reader.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> Know I ſtand condemned at the barre</l>
                  <l>Of thy beſt judgement, but I know they are</l>
                  <l>Not yet in print, who can eſcape the tongue</l>
                  <l>Of thy detractions, or can ſhun the wrong</l>
                  <l>Of thy invectives and the wicked ſpight,</l>
                  <l>Which thou pronounceth unto ſuch as write:</l>
                  <l>The froward Curre who nothing can but bark,</l>
                  <l>Thou dost reſemble, and the ſelf ſame mark,</l>
                  <l>Makes me provide for to prevent the worſt,</l>
                  <l>To ſave my ſelf, though thou with barking burſt,</l>
                  <l>Thou thinkſt to vent thy wiſdom if thou prate,</l>
                  <l>But thou expreſſes ignorance in that:</l>
                  <l>Thy Criticks carping crackt braind bragging words,</l>
                  <l>Nothing but poor deſpightfulnes affords:</l>
                  <l>And Ime perſwaded thou wilt be ſo brief,</l>
                  <l>Thou'lt cenſure me, before thou readſt a leaf:</l>
                  <l>It is an eaſie task for to traduce,</l>
                  <l>And in my abſence for to threat abuſe:</l>
                  <l>It's alſo common for to carp by thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who ſcarce have ſence of ſmelling in their noſe;</l>
                  <l>The Actor's alwaies readieſt in his rage,</l>
                  <l>For to be beaten from his acting ſtage:</l>
                  <l>The horſe who hath not eyes for to direct</l>
                  <l>Him in the way, well raſhly break his neck.</l>
                  <l>And thou who ſcarcely hath a noſe to ſmell,</l>
                  <l>Or eyes to ſee, or knowledge for to tell</l>
                  <l>What now thou readſt, or on the ſtage can ſay</l>
                  <l>That was a bad, or this a better play:</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt preſume thy verdict for to ſpend</l>
                  <l>At my expreſsions, and darſt vilipend</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:10"/>My Muſes labours, though thou ſpeak in vain,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend the iſſues of thy empty brain.</l>
                  <l>This is the beſt, thy idle words may wander,</l>
                  <l>Thy tongue will never be accounted ſtander.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis a thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not account ſo ſmall,</l>
                  <l>Nor love to ſeem ſo ſuperficiall,</l>
                  <l>As for to paſſe it for thy partiall word,</l>
                  <l>But dare and will maintain it with my ſword.</l>
                  <l>Nor do I ſpeak becauſe I love or hate,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſpend my time at any ſuch like rate:</l>
                  <l>But meerly venture with indifferent eye,</l>
                  <l>And from a heart full of ſincerity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth know my fault, much better it may be,</l>
                  <l>Then thou who art ſo bold to cenſure me,</l>
                  <l>I erre in nothing that I do intend,</l>
                  <l>But that my knowledge cannot comprehend</l>
                  <l>The height of his deſervings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when I ſtrive</l>
                  <l>For to recount his vertues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and contrive</l>
                  <l>Within the compaſſe of my Muſes skill,</l>
                  <l>His actions, ſurely herein do I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ill:</l>
                  <l>But this it is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in witnes of my love,</l>
                  <l>And I affection more then faſhion move:</l>
                  <l>Therefore forbear, and touch not on the quick,</l>
                  <l>There are Commanders numerous, and thick,</l>
                  <l>And thouſands more of Souldiers are abroad,</l>
                  <l>Of diſpoſitions deſparate, and odd,</l>
                  <l>Who bears about them wears it as a badge,</l>
                  <l>The name of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> O! do not inrage</l>
                  <l>The multitude; for they were ever all</l>
                  <l>So much ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ted to their Generall,</l>
                  <l>And He was alwaies as the fixed ſtarre,</l>
                  <l>About the which all others placed are:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:10"/>For to attend, of whom they took delight,</l>
                  <l>And followed all couragiouſly to ſight:</l>
                  <l>To have a Leader ſo belov'd, an Earle,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe vertues were more glorious then a Pearle</l>
                  <l>Of rich eſteem, or ſuch a noble Lord,</l>
                  <l>To ſing whoſe praiſe all Chriſtendom accord:</l>
                  <l>It is a fault in me, I do confeſſe,</l>
                  <l>To undertake it ſurely I tranſgreſſe,</l>
                  <l>And do deſerve to be condemnd but then,</l>
                  <l>Let me intreat thee for to take the pen,</l>
                  <l>And where into thou ſees I do offend,</l>
                  <l>Do but ſo much my errors to amend:</l>
                  <l>Which if thou doſt, I can no more require:</l>
                  <l>My Patrons praiſe is all I do deſire.</l>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>Ad Eundem.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I See I once more muſt be cenſur'd yet,</l>
                        <l>But I am armed for to anſwer it:</l>
                        <l>I know thou thinkſt the entry of the peece</l>
                        <l>Is almoſt bigger then the Edifice.</l>
                        <l>To this, I ſay, rich jew'ls, though they be ſmall,</l>
                        <l>Muſt have ſtrong gates, be compaſt with a wall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <hi>VVilliam Mercer.</hi> Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I'm reall receiv' me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I'm reall, receiv' me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> or elſe, if not,</l>
                        <l>I will not be receiv'd by ſuch a ſot.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="encomia_to_himself">
                  <div type="sonnet">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:11"/>
                     <head>In commendation of the Author, and his worke. To Himſelfe.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>FRom that repreſentation, which in this</l>
                        <l>Your mirror of the worth of others, is</l>
                        <l>Vnto our view expoſed, doth reflect</l>
                        <l>The Image of your ſelf, in an aſpect</l>
                        <l>More ſemblable, then ever Looking-Glaſſe</l>
                        <l>Did ſhew the beauty of a Ladies face.</l>
                        <l>Then ſeeing that the picture of your merit,</l>
                        <l>Can by the penſil of no other ſpirit</l>
                        <l>Be drawn ſo to the life, for that theſe lines</l>
                        <l>Set forth your ſplendour, ev'n as your name ſhines</l>
                        <l>In their contexture, making you, and your</l>
                        <l>Poaems be either th'others portraiture,</l>
                        <l>It ſhall ſuffice me onely to avow,</l>
                        <l>That you renown the book, and the book you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>T. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="sonnet">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:11"/>
                     <head>The Author to his worke, and in relation to the former lines.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>IHave created, made, and chriſtned thee,</l>
                        <l>Thou haſt thy being, all thou art, of mee:</l>
                        <l>I beſt know what's inclos'd in thy contents,</l>
                        <l>And to beholders, what thou repreſents,</l>
                        <l>Yet is the leaſt part of the praiſe but due</l>
                        <l>To me, the honour wholy doth accrue</l>
                        <l>Vnto the ſubſtance whereof thou art made,</l>
                        <l>So purely fine, becauſe had I not had</l>
                        <l>Such quinteſſences, rarify'd, and fine,</l>
                        <l>For to compoſe rhee of, no skill was mine,</l>
                        <l>To make thee ſo, in luſtre, pure, and rare,</l>
                        <l>So abſolute, ſo curious, ſingular:</l>
                        <l>Then as mine own I freely ſpeak to thee,</l>
                        <l>But thy perfections challenge more of mee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="prologue">
                  <pb facs="tcp:113472:12"/>
                  <head>The Prologue to this enſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
                  <l>THe <hi>Author</hi> firſt doth invocate the <hi>Nine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To aid him with intelligence divine:</l>
                  <l>Then enters in a <hi>Civil</hi> threefold <hi>VVarre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And fights through al the forces which there are</l>
                  <l>Preſenteth divers <hi>Actors,</hi> though not all,</l>
                  <l>Fomenters of this Story Tragicall:</l>
                  <l>Promotes the City, parlies for a peace:</l>
                  <l>And puts the Kingdom in a better caſe,</l>
                  <l>VVhich done, to raiſe this Ilands endleſſe glory,</l>
                  <l>He ſhews ſome worthies, &amp; breaks of the ſtory.</l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:12"/>
                     <head>ANGLIAE PECVLVM. <hi>OR</hi> ENGLANDS LOOKING-GLASSE.</head>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Come and aid mee, teach me to indite,</l>
                     <l>Inſpire my Muſe, inſtruct me for to write,</l>
                     <l>Come all you ſiſters of the ſacred nine,</l>
                     <l>Infuſe in me, your vertues moſt divine;</l>
                     <l>Bow down the branches of Parnaſſus bow's,</l>
                     <l>And give me thereby ſtrength to tell my vows</l>
                     <l>Afford me favour (that I may go on)</l>
                     <l>To taſt the waters of ſweet Haelicon.</l>
                     <l>I undertake to tell of civil wars,</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch diſaſters, and diſtracted jarrs,</l>
                     <l>I tell a ſtory Tragi Comicall:</l>
                     <l>And ſing the praiſes of my Generall.</l>
                     <l>I do preſume a little, now and then</l>
                     <l>To tell the acts of Englands worthy men</l>
                     <l>Although in weaknes, willing am to ſhow,</l>
                     <l>How much affection, England I do owe,</l>
                     <l>What great regard my inclination bears</l>
                     <l>Unto its noble and renowned Peers:</l>
                     <l>With what reſpect I labour to preſent</l>
                     <l>My duty to the Houſe of Parliament:</l>
                     <l>And theſe Committees, ſet for to attend</l>
                     <l>All grievances: I alſo recommend</l>
                     <l>(Without deceit, of my impartiall pen)</l>
                     <l>The endleſſe vertues of ſome martiall men.</l>
                     <l>I ſhew the ſufferings of a glorious City,</l>
                     <l>Their vaſt expences, and their endleſſe pity:</l>
                     <l>I tell the travells of thoſe deep divines,</l>
                     <l>Too high a task, for my unlearned lines:</l>
                     <l>I do invent a ſecond way, and ſet</l>
                     <l>A Glaſſe before thee, wherein I do let</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:13"/>Thee ſee ſuch things, though by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>econd fight,</l>
                     <l>As cannot well be repreſented right,</l>
                     <l>I do report the praiſes of the day,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Mars</hi> ſet meetings, and I truly ſay,</l>
                     <l>I undertake to tell thee with my pen:</l>
                     <l>The actions of ten hundred thouſand men.</l>
                     <l>Nor is this all, my running pen denotes</l>
                     <l>The famous Lords, commiſſioners for the Scots</l>
                     <l>With their aſſiſtants, morall, and divine:</l>
                     <l>A glance of each, within this glaſſe of mine,</l>
                     <l>My travels do extend themſelves, as farre</l>
                     <l>From hence, as to the fixed North pole ſtarre,</l>
                     <l>A triple travel do I alſo take,</l>
                     <l>And in that Iriſh Iland Journey make,</l>
                     <l>This is a labour for a larger wit,</l>
                     <l>Excuſe me therefore, if I fail in it.</l>
                     <l>It was the yeer ſix hundred thirty nine,</l>
                     <l>When firſt we ſaw theſe evils to incline:</l>
                     <l>This angry ſtorme aroſe firſt in the North,</l>
                     <l>And thence its force in violence ſent forth,</l>
                     <l>Till it infected <hi>Englands</hi> banks about,</l>
                     <l>From Eaſt, to Weſt, the South, and North throughout,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Iriſh Iland</hi> which I treat upon</l>
                     <l>Was likewiſe bent in this combuſtion,</l>
                     <l>A threefold cord in ſuch a curſed cauſe,</l>
                     <l>So ſtrongly linkt to overthrow the laws,</l>
                     <l>Subjects of one united <hi>Diadem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As if their Soveraign had invited them,</l>
                     <l>All were combin'd, and in this baſe deſigne,</l>
                     <l>As is apparent in this glaſſe of mine.</l>
                     <l>Two mighty great incendiaries meet</l>
                     <l>In this rebellion, each another greet,</l>
                     <l>A skilfull, cunning, curſed <hi>Machiavil.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Joynd with the wiſdom of <hi>Achitophel:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The one a <hi>Depute,</hi> meerly ſet aſide,</l>
                     <l>To ruine all, by <hi>Diabolick</hi> pride.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:13"/>The other was, chief Metropolitan,</l>
                     <l>Within whoſe breaſt this buſines began<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Theſe were the men who undertook the thing,</l>
                     <l>Pretending all in honour of the King:</l>
                     <l>Did lay aſide the loyall bond of peace:</l>
                     <l>And priviledges of the preſent place;</l>
                     <l>Forgot the glory of the great <hi>Creator,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This Prelat who ſhouldſt prov'd a <hi>Mediator,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Joynd with this <hi>Iudas,</hi> in his Maſters caſe</l>
                     <l>For to betraid him, in his very face,</l>
                     <l>But yet behold, theſe <hi>Machiavilians</hi> were</l>
                     <l>For all the wicked waies they could prepare,</l>
                     <l>Found out, and forc'd for to imbrace the end</l>
                     <l>They did for others treacherouſly intend,</l>
                     <l>They ſought to curb the honour of that God,</l>
                     <l>Who did prevent them by his angry rod:</l>
                     <l>Strove to deſtroy Religion, in pretence</l>
                     <l>That all was for Religions defence:</l>
                     <l>This is the work I undertake to write,</l>
                     <l>O! give me knowledge, and a perfect ſight<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of ſuch aſſiſtance, as I ſhall deſire,</l>
                     <l>In flame my Muſe with that Coeleſtiall fire,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhall afford me, what I ſtand in need,</l>
                     <l>And what ſhall ſerve them, who deſire to read,</l>
                     <l>According to the nature of the thing:</l>
                     <l>O! add ſome ſtrength unto my feeble wing.</l>
                     <l>That I may fly, before my feathers tire,</l>
                     <l>To tell the truth, where only I aſpire:</l>
                     <l>And for to ſpeak in order, let me enter:</l>
                     <l>Firſt, at thoſe worthies, who did give adventure,</l>
                     <l>In legall manner, with a mighty hand,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Potentates, and plots for to withſtand:</l>
                     <l>See how the God of order did them bleſſe,</l>
                     <l>Who ſought by order, and prevented this:</l>
                     <l>They cald a counſell of the higheſt kind,</l>
                     <l>There to aſſiſted, by their Soveraignes mind,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:14"/>And by conſent of the imperiall power,</l>
                     <l>Committed theſe Confederates to the Tower,</l>
                     <l>But they had done the worſt that they could do,</l>
                     <l>According to the bad intents of two:</l>
                     <l>Had turnd the juſt intentions of the State,</l>
                     <l>To be conceiv'd, cauſe of their Soveraigns hate:</l>
                     <l>Had ſet the Nations all three, by the ears,</l>
                     <l>Sweld up their hearts with jealouſies, and fears,</l>
                     <l>Till in the end, they were arraignd, derided,</l>
                     <l>Accus'd, condemnd, and both of them beheaded</l>
                     <l>Yet did that ſeed, which they had ſown about,</l>
                     <l>Spring in ſuch plenty, and did take ſuch root:</l>
                     <l>That like thoſe trees, whence are the branches lopt,</l>
                     <l>Or as thoſe weeds, the oftner they are cropt,</l>
                     <l>Increaſe the more, ſo did thoſe rebels riſe,</l>
                     <l>Like moats into the Sun, before our eyes,</l>
                     <l>But here's their craft, their Soveraign they incenſe,</l>
                     <l>He muſt ſuſpect his Parliament, go hence,</l>
                     <l>They do perſwade him, if he will deny,</l>
                     <l>The royall preſence of his Majeſty:</l>
                     <l>Their was no Law to authorize their actions,</l>
                     <l>But that they would diſſolve in ſudden factions,</l>
                     <l>This was the doctrine that they taught the King</l>
                     <l>Although there was no warrant for ſuch thing,</l>
                     <l>For notwithſtanding ſtatutes do ordain</l>
                     <l>Kings to confirm, yet are they not in vain:</l>
                     <l>Although their Soveraign contrair to that truſt</l>
                     <l>The Laws allow him, ſhun them through his luſt</l>
                     <l>But as the members without a head muſt fall,</l>
                     <l>The King and Subjects, are reciprocall.</l>
                     <l>Yet Kingdoms can be ruled, by a thing</l>
                     <l>Calld Civil Laws, albe't there be no King;</l>
                     <l>But will you tell me? can a King do ſo,</l>
                     <l>Without a Law? or rule aright, or no)</l>
                     <l>No, no, a Law without a King can be,</l>
                     <l>But Kings without a Law, you cannot ſee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:14"/>It is much ſafer to enjoy a Law</l>
                     <l>Without a Soveraign, if he will withdraw,</l>
                     <l>Then if a Land be ſubject to that cruel</l>
                     <l>Command of Kings, where is no Law to rule:</l>
                     <l>But as the body's joyned with the mind,</l>
                     <l>And as the tree is coupled to the rinde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>So ſhould the Soveraign, and the Subject too,</l>
                     <l>Agree in one, do what each other do.</l>
                     <l>But this was that, which they tell him, he muſt</l>
                     <l>Or do, or elſe he nothing hath to truſt:</l>
                     <l>Vpon ſuch bad inſtructions, he retires,</l>
                     <l>Forſakes the Counſels, and the juſt deſires</l>
                     <l>Of his ingenuous Court of Parliament:</l>
                     <l>Which did provoke, a fearfull detriment</l>
                     <l>Unto his Highneſſe, and that dignity</l>
                     <l>Which doth belong unto his Majeſty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>For his great Counſel, by his high command,</l>
                     <l>Kept conſtant meetings, with a mighty hand,</l>
                     <l>And by his Law, did iſſue out their orders</l>
                     <l>In every corner of the Kingdoms borders:</l>
                     <l>Requiring thereby, ſubjects to ſubmit,</l>
                     <l>And render due obedience unto it:</l>
                     <l>And to give ſtrength unto their juſt intents,</l>
                     <l>They raiſed Armies by commandements:</l>
                     <l>For to regain their gracious royall prince,</l>
                     <l>To vindicate their honours, and convince</l>
                     <l>Thoſe errors, which were in their King inſpir'd</l>
                     <l>And this was that they conſtantly deſir'd:</l>
                     <l>But yet one paſſage muſt I not forget,</l>
                     <l>Into its higheſt nature to relate.</l>
                     <l>They do incenſe, to make the breach the more,</l>
                     <l>Their Soveraign, for to approach the door</l>
                     <l>Of Parliament, and there would take the embers,</l>
                     <l>Deſtroy the body, cutting off the members:</l>
                     <l>Accompanied with proud pernicious foes,</l>
                     <l>Call'd Cavaliers, from whence their name aroſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:15"/>This was their plot: more hatefull to be held,</l>
                     <l>Then was that powder treaſon paraleld:</l>
                     <l>For that was by our enemies abroad,</l>
                     <l>But this by thoſe confeſt the ſelf ſame God:</l>
                     <l>That was by powder, to diſpatch with ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>All in an inſtant: hereby might they bleed</l>
                     <l>Above an Ocean, iſſuing every day</l>
                     <l>Forth from their ſides, who I dare truly ſay,</l>
                     <l>Sought by all means for to maintain the ſence</l>
                     <l>Of ancient ſtatutes, and their Kings defence:</l>
                     <l>O! higheſt, horrid, maſſacre of hell,</l>
                     <l>It makes me tremble, when I ſtrive to tell:</l>
                     <l>But am reviv'd, O! how my ſpirits fill</l>
                     <l>With joy and gladneſſe, when I ſaw this ill</l>
                     <l>So wiſely ſhund: O! but a ſecret hand</l>
                     <l>Of power divine, did do't I underſtand,</l>
                     <l>But hereupon our Soveraign thought it right</l>
                     <l>Himſelf for to ſequeſtrate from the ſight</l>
                     <l>And preſence of this higheſt Parliament;</l>
                     <l>Inſpir'd with fury of fierce diſcontent:</l>
                     <l>Then as the child, who ſees an angry Father,</l>
                     <l>Or like ſuch loyall loving ſubjects rather,</l>
                     <l>Or like the chaſt imbraces of a ſpouſe,</l>
                     <l>Who prayes, perſwades, ſolicites, and ſhe woes,</l>
                     <l>A wilfull husband, when he will divorce,</l>
                     <l>Or her abandon, or which may be worſe,</l>
                     <l>Accuſe her of a breach, and urge upon her</l>
                     <l>Thoſe inſolencies of a baſe diſhonour:</l>
                     <l>She ſtill purſues, importunes, pleads, and ſpeaks,</l>
                     <l>And on her knees, ſubmiſſively ſhe ſeeks</l>
                     <l>To reconcile her thoughts to his again:</l>
                     <l>But all her time and tears are ſpent in vain:</l>
                     <l>Theſe free-born ſubjects, like to thoſe, I ſay,</l>
                     <l>They ſeek their Soveraign, and they humbly pray:</l>
                     <l>They do petition, and they call on high</l>
                     <l>Upon the maker of his Majeſty:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:15"/>Into whoſe hands the hearts of Princes be,</l>
                     <l>He would be pleaſd to move him, let him ſee</l>
                     <l>Their zealous hearts, with what affection</l>
                     <l>They would ſubmit unto his ſacred throne,</l>
                     <l>If he would pleaſe but condiſcend to ſtay,</l>
                     <l>And ratifie thoſe actions, which ſay they,</l>
                     <l>Shall be determin'd, after to the lawes</l>
                     <l>In former times, in every point, and clauſe:</l>
                     <l>The priviledges of your Majeſty</l>
                     <l>Shall be eſtabliſht in a high degree:</l>
                     <l>We will contrive as lines of law ſhall lead,</l>
                     <l>Your Highnes ſhall corroborate, as head.</l>
                     <l>But all is nothing, lo, he ſtops his eare;</l>
                     <l>Retires himſelf, and leaves them ſitting there:</l>
                     <l>Conveens huge Armies, on a fair pretence,</l>
                     <l>That all was for his perſonal defence.</l>
                     <l>Then in the wiſdom of that Councell great,</l>
                     <l>Which was eſtabliſht in its proper right,</l>
                     <l>Whence he remoov'd, they ſent an army out</l>
                     <l>For to defend the faith, its foes to rout:</l>
                     <l>Their banners were bedect with holy phraſes,</l>
                     <l>And in their marches ſung their maſters praiſes:</l>
                     <l>And to prevent more imminent miſchief,</l>
                     <l>They went and waited for the next relief:</l>
                     <l>Had no commiſſion, if conceiv'd aright,</l>
                     <l>But to defend, not to inforce a fight:</l>
                     <l>Elſe had they often, if not ſo reſtraind,</l>
                     <l>Reduc'd theſe ſad diviſions which remaind.</l>
                     <l>They were commanded by that famous Lord,</l>
                     <l>Who by the leaſt neglect, did not debord.</l>
                     <l>The firſt, or great encounter which was ſeen,</l>
                     <l>Was by <hi>Edge hill,</hi> ſo nam'd, or <hi>Kenton green:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'T may be ſome meetings fortun'd for to fall</l>
                     <l>Between two parties, which I do not call</l>
                     <l>To mind; but here the onely place was ſet,</l>
                     <l>Where theſe two Royall armies fiercely met:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:16"/>It was the year ſix hundred forty two,</l>
                     <l>The twenty three <hi>October,</hi> when they do</l>
                     <l>Draw up their forces, on the Sabbath day:</l>
                     <l>I was a witneſſe, therefore dare I ſay;</l>
                     <l>I will not ſeem ſo partiall with my quill,</l>
                     <l>For feud, nor favour, nor for no mans ill,</l>
                     <l>But will declare ſuch as I then did ſee,</l>
                     <l>Or as my charge ſometimes permitted me:</l>
                     <l>The royall preſence once prepar'd, approach'd,</l>
                     <l>Vnmounted from his horſe, or elſe uncoach'd:</l>
                     <l>Gave orders to his chief Commanders then,</l>
                     <l>To ſhew themſelves couragious, valiant men,</l>
                     <l>This did I hear by true report, and I</l>
                     <l>May well avouch, they, herein do notly:</l>
                     <l>Then with the ſound of trumpets, and the noiſe</l>
                     <l>Of Drums, and Canons, and a mighty voice</l>
                     <l>Of Souldiers threatnings, thirſting after blood,</l>
                     <l>Did cover all the fields, as a cloud;</l>
                     <l>Came on, gave fire, purſued, and they ſet</l>
                     <l>Themſelves at worke; and were as fiercely met:</l>
                     <l>For though we had not orders to purſue:</l>
                     <l>Yet muſt they not tryumph, I tell you true;</l>
                     <l>Their banners were with wickednes adornd,</l>
                     <l>Our holy enſignes ſinfully they ſcornd:</l>
                     <l>Yet once ingag'd ſincerely I proteſt,</l>
                     <l>They fought with courage, while the battel laſt,</l>
                     <l>But was conſtrained for to give us ground,</l>
                     <l>As by their abſence in the morning found:</l>
                     <l>Fled from their peeces, left their dead behind them,</l>
                     <l>And at ſuch diſtance as we could not find:</l>
                     <l>The royall Standard, this day did we gain,</l>
                     <l>Lord <hi>Lindſey</hi> Gen'rall in the field was ſlain:</l>
                     <l>Took divers Enſignes, placed them to fly</l>
                     <l>As Emblems, Trophees, of our victory:</l>
                     <l>With certain thouſands of the vulgar ſort,</l>
                     <l>Which were deſtroyd, yet they, for to be ſhort,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:16"/>Conceiv'd a ſhadow of a ſecond ſtrength:</l>
                     <l>As broken reeds, which faild them: in the length</l>
                     <l>Approacht in preſence of fair <hi>Londons</hi> walls,</l>
                     <l>Expect relief; but liſten what befalls<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>For on another Sabbath day they ſought</l>
                     <l>Advantage, but it treacherouſly was wrought:</l>
                     <l>Becauſe they had a conference between</l>
                     <l>Their chiefeſt men, and ours, and we did mean</l>
                     <l>Upon the paſſing of each faithfull word,</l>
                     <l>That none ſhould dare for to unſheath a ſword:</l>
                     <l>Yet notwithſtanding that they had ingag'd</l>
                     <l>Upon a treaty, and their honour pledg'd;</l>
                     <l>On this pretence they did approach, and are</l>
                     <l>In armes at hand; bad ſtratagem in Warre:</l>
                     <l>To ſtain their honour, or to violate:</l>
                     <l>The truſt impos'd, ſhould be immaculate.</l>
                     <l>But what advantage gaind they by this act?</l>
                     <l>Their mighty Army very nigh was ſackt:</l>
                     <l>For had they not in ſecret of the night,</l>
                     <l>As formerly, returned while they might:</l>
                     <l>Their many thouſands, both of Horſe and Foot;</l>
                     <l>And in the which they truſted, were ſo ſtout,</l>
                     <l>Were very like to be confounded then,</l>
                     <l>Such was the minds of our heroick men:</l>
                     <l>For they confided, firſt, to find ſupply</l>
                     <l>From out the City, elſe had they not come nigh.</l>
                     <l>But all their plots were diſappointed, ſo</l>
                     <l>That they were glad with greedines to go:</l>
                     <l>For <hi>London</hi> long'd their Soveraign to enjoy,</l>
                     <l>But ſhund to let them enter to deſtroy</l>
                     <l>Themſelves, and ſhopps, their houſes, and their ware:</l>
                     <l>No, they reſolv'd they ſhould not enter there.</l>
                     <l>Thus muſt they march: to make the matter worſe,</l>
                     <l>They preſſe the people; and they plunder horſe:</l>
                     <l>They do pretend they ſeck the Subjects good,</l>
                     <l>As innocents, they ſhun to ſhed their blood.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:17"/>The Papiſts have preheminence at Court,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Jeſuits</hi> have <hi>Jeſus,</hi> to be ſhort:</l>
                     <l>They pray unto thoſe Idols, but pretend</l>
                     <l>The Proteſtant profeſſion they defend:</l>
                     <l>Their God is blind, ſo are they alſo too;</l>
                     <l>He cannot help, nor know they what to do:</l>
                     <l>This God of theirs deceives them, yet will they</l>
                     <l>Create a new Creator every day;</l>
                     <l>Such means as thoſe they uſe to move the people,</l>
                     <l>And rings Religion out of every ſteeple:</l>
                     <l>They make a proceſſe in impious actions,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrive to bring the Common wealth in factions:</l>
                     <l>The ſcope of all their carriage abroad;</l>
                     <l>Hath prov'd but high deriſion to God:</l>
                     <l>For whatſoever from the ſource was ſent</l>
                     <l>Of good Religion, with a ſtrong intent:</l>
                     <l>They trod it under footſteps, and did fly</l>
                     <l>The happines of true divinity:</l>
                     <l>Thus did they ſpend the power they did contract</l>
                     <l>To ruine Goſpel, bring the beſt to wrack:</l>
                     <l>For let me ask, as one who hath an eye</l>
                     <l>And pen, free of impartiality:</l>
                     <l>What did they do in all their great proceedings?</l>
                     <l>Or what perceive you in your by paſt readings?</l>
                     <l>'Tis true they ſought, and manfully did ſtand;</l>
                     <l>But it was moſt becauſe of good command:</l>
                     <l>And ſo they rangd in moſt unruly kind,</l>
                     <l>With ſtretcht out armes, and irteligious mind:</l>
                     <l>Till at each meeting, by the ſword, or power;</l>
                     <l>We took them captives, or we did devour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The chiefeſt of their Champions, uncontrold;</l>
                     <l>Which made their armies by their preſence bold</l>
                     <l>Yet notwithſtanding that they are ſo ſtout<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Chivalry are ruind, and the foot</l>
                     <l>Are forc'd to fly, or in the end muſt yeeld,</l>
                     <l>But for the moſt part was an equall field:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:17"/>I attribute, next, to th'Almighties hand</l>
                     <l>As I have ſaid, all to their wiſe Command;</l>
                     <l>For had they not, that high renowned <hi>Scot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Surnamed <hi>Ruthen,</hi> Earl, a man of note,</l>
                     <l>Their Generall; and of that Nation many</l>
                     <l>As brave Commanders, in the world as any,</l>
                     <l>Beſides, their high determinations ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>When they perceive their richeſt ſpoils decreaſe:</l>
                     <l>Their hands did fail them, and their hearts relented<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>It was too late, or elſe they had repented.</l>
                     <l>They knew the cauſe wherein they had been bent,</l>
                     <l>Was contrary to the Laws commandment:</l>
                     <l>And that they had no warrant from the Word</l>
                     <l>Of God, nor did it privilege afford,</l>
                     <l>Unto their perſons for to interpoſe</l>
                     <l>Between their Soveraign, and the ſeed of thoſe</l>
                     <l>Who were elected, in a legall band</l>
                     <l>As one united body, for to ſtand.</l>
                     <l>And now you ſee, when power is in our hand</l>
                     <l>By full Commiſſion, abſolute command,</l>
                     <l>How they are vanquiſh'd, Towns regained, ſo</l>
                     <l>But if you ask me how, I do not know.</l>
                     <l>Thus from this place of powerfull reſidence</l>
                     <l>To that, where <hi>Phebus</hi> leaves his influence;</l>
                     <l>Both Towns, and Countrey, once, which did ſubmit,</l>
                     <l>Were gaind into obedience of it:</l>
                     <l>Of it, I ſay, which ſhould our actions guide,</l>
                     <l>And from the which, our thoughts ſhould never ſlide.</l>
                     <l>Likewiſe their ſtrength, extended to the North,</l>
                     <l>Throughout the Kingdom, reached over forth;</l>
                     <l>But by the way, oppoſed were by might</l>
                     <l>With multitudes, and millions in their ſight;</l>
                     <l>That all were as, the ſtubble to the fire,</l>
                     <l>Or as the duſt which from the winde retire.</l>
                     <l>Some were confounded, others forc'd to fly,</l>
                     <l>Their bodies wounded all were glad to cry,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:18"/>And beg for pardon, ſafe it were thoſe Prieſts</l>
                     <l>And Jeſuits, who counted all but jeaſts</l>
                     <l>Till they were routed, totally, and then</l>
                     <l>They ſaw their Gods, were given prayes to men.</l>
                     <l>This did expreſſe the providence, and wit</l>
                     <l>Of prudent <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who appointed it,</l>
                     <l>By vertue of, His Warrant from his hand,</l>
                     <l>Which gave all others, abſolute Command</l>
                     <l>As high, immediate, onely Generall:</l>
                     <l>Nor do I ſeek to derogate at all,</l>
                     <l>From thoſe, whoſe actions were approv'd to be</l>
                     <l>Heroick, noble, vertuous, yet let me</l>
                     <l>Without offence, give every one their own,</l>
                     <l>Nor give my Generall, but what well is known</l>
                     <l>To be, and is, and ever ſhall be due,</l>
                     <l>His proper pow'r, I will a vouch it true,</l>
                     <l>Yet this is not the ſcope of my intent,</l>
                     <l>My pen importunes, and my Muſe is bent</l>
                     <l>To take her flight fair <hi>Albion</hi> throughout,</l>
                     <l>From Eaſt to Weſt, its borders round about;</l>
                     <l>Nor reſts ſhe there, but lo my <hi>Muſe</hi> ſhe muſt</l>
                     <l>Travers the waters, and in ſecret thruſt</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf, amongſt ſuch as count nothing juſt;</l>
                     <l>But what's invented by their wicked luſt.</l>
                     <l>And what by them is acted, and reſolv'd,</l>
                     <l>Though they themſelves, are thereby much involv'd</l>
                     <l>In wofull ſin; yet they forſake with ſhame</l>
                     <l>The noble title, of a I oyall Name.</l>
                     <l>They do deny the pow'r, and vertue too</l>
                     <l>Of Covenants, and this they likewayes do</l>
                     <l>Deny the truth, nor will they entertain</l>
                     <l>A Triple Crown, but labours to ordain</l>
                     <l>By private factions, what they think is fit,</l>
                     <l>According to their diabolick wit:</l>
                     <l>And this they call a Covenant, becauſe</l>
                     <l>They covenant, to contradict the Laws:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:18"/>Lay's truth aſide, forſakes the God of peace,</l>
                     <l>Abandons vertue, wickedneſſe embreace.</l>
                     <l>They cut the throats of ſuch as are not Rebels,</l>
                     <l>And will not bow to their pernicious bables.</l>
                     <l>Thus have they run, and rang'd, five falls almoſt,</l>
                     <l>Triumphed o'er poore Proteſtants, and croſt,</l>
                     <l>Yea, and tormented, Innocents, and ſuch</l>
                     <l>As had not knowledge to diſcern, nor which</l>
                     <l>Was good, or bad, was right or wrong, nor what</l>
                     <l>Was to be choſen, or be aymed at.</l>
                     <l>All were alike in their polluted hearts,</l>
                     <l>They pierc'd the ſides of Infants with their darts:</l>
                     <l>Began, go on, and entertains a war;</l>
                     <l>And thoſe are they, 'gainſt whom this Nation are</l>
                     <l>So well ingag'd, and daily doth ſend over</l>
                     <l>Supplyes of all things, them for to recover;</l>
                     <l>What vaſt expences, in a boundleſſe meaſure,</l>
                     <l>Enough to have exhauſted <hi>Chryſus</hi> treaſure.</l>
                     <l>Millions of men, and multitudes in ſtore,</l>
                     <l>The more is ſpent, they ſtill imploy the more:</l>
                     <l>And all is furniſh'd, by this famous place,</l>
                     <l>The Metrapole of <hi>England,</hi> and the grace,</l>
                     <l>Yea, and the glory, of the worlds delight,</l>
                     <l>For ſumptuous buildings, wonders to the ſight.</l>
                     <l>To what ſhall I endeavour to compare</l>
                     <l>The excellencies of this place ſo rare?</l>
                     <l>Whoſe beautie ſhines, whoſe glory is ſo great,</l>
                     <l>That I ſhould rob it, of its proper right,</l>
                     <l>If I ſhould lay it in the Scales to try</l>
                     <l>If any be of ſuch equality;</l>
                     <l>But what my <hi>Muſe,</hi> are theſe the news thou brings?</l>
                     <l>Canſt tell us nothing, but ſuch dolefull things?</l>
                     <l>As Kingdoms ruins, nothing but of war,</l>
                     <l>And what is worſe, if any worſer are:</l>
                     <l>O, yes, the waters are abated much,</l>
                     <l>The evils are not now ſo bad; but ſuch</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:19"/>As thou mayſt ſee, the deep deluge is dry,</l>
                     <l>The Ark is opened, and I can eſpie</l>
                     <l>A peacefull Dove, tranſporting in her bill</l>
                     <l>An Olive branch, directed by the will</l>
                     <l>Of that divine, high wiſdom of that God,</l>
                     <l>To tell them this, who in the Ark abode,</l>
                     <l>The floods are fled into their former bounds;</l>
                     <l>We can perceive the waters from the grounds:</l>
                     <l>The Sun doth ſhine, diſperſed are the clouds,</l>
                     <l>The ſtormes are calm'd, abated are the floods.</l>
                     <l>The Ark of <hi>England,</hi> doth in ſafetie ſtand,</l>
                     <l>The Creatures enjoy a peacefull Land.</l>
                     <l>Now are we fully ſatisfide, and more</l>
                     <l>Then ever we could be at all before,</l>
                     <l>That this deſtruction was by divine Hand</l>
                     <l>To waſh away the wicked from the Land.</l>
                     <l>For was not God derided to his face?</l>
                     <l>His Laws neglected, miſregarded grace:</l>
                     <l>Pride was become ſuperlative, and I</l>
                     <l>May well avouch, that baſe hypocriſie</l>
                     <l>Was plac'd within the very breaſts of all</l>
                     <l>Both rich, and poore; the greater ſort, and ſmall</l>
                     <l>Were all infected: and the height of ſin,</l>
                     <l>When God forbore a while, increaſt therein.</l>
                     <l>That ſhould I reckon, irreligion, lyes,</l>
                     <l>The ſin of Murther, and adulterous eyes,</l>
                     <l>Contempt, deceit, and all the ſins of hell</l>
                     <l>Raign'd in this Nation, in the which we dwell.</l>
                     <l>But now all tokens of a peacefull time,</l>
                     <l>That we are cleanſed from the guilt, or crime</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe offences, wherewith we were cloy'd;</l>
                     <l>And for the which, we well nigh were deſtroy'd.</l>
                     <l>Approach, and do preſent themſelves at hand,</l>
                     <l>And do proclaim, a quiet peacefull Land:</l>
                     <l>Our bloody battels have brought better things,</l>
                     <l>The Subjects thoughts, united to the Kings.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:19"/>Our former evils, avarice, and greed,</l>
                     <l>And all thoſe ſins which heretofore you read,</l>
                     <l>Are now ſo blotted, and abated too,</l>
                     <l>That what they did before, they no more do;</l>
                     <l>So are the thoughts now of our Soveraign turn'd,</l>
                     <l>For which the Land, and all thats therein mourn'd;</l>
                     <l>That what the Subject ſought, and much entreated,</l>
                     <l>And by unceſſaut Meſſengers invited;</l>
                     <l>Yet were deny'd, now is it freely ſent</l>
                     <l>To be embraced by the <hi>Parlament.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The King and Subject now are almoſt one,</l>
                     <l>The way to make the moſt Magnifique Throne</l>
                     <l>That ever was, or in this Land hath been,</l>
                     <l>Or heretofore by any hath been ſeen.</l>
                     <l>O happie time, may I be bold to tell,</l>
                     <l>Within the which this great diſcention fell;</l>
                     <l>Which is ſo like to gain ſo great a good,</l>
                     <l>Though we have bought it dearly, by our blood.</l>
                     <l>Religion's aym'd at, in a truer kind,</l>
                     <l>If we can get them all but of a mind;</l>
                     <l>Our errours are removed, all intend</l>
                     <l>Their former frailties fully to amend;</l>
                     <l>So that the evils of our by-paſt age</l>
                     <l>Shall gain us far more faithfull privilege:</l>
                     <l>And make us further, to forſake the ſin</l>
                     <l>Which heretofore we ſo were wallowed in:</l>
                     <l>Shall make us know, whence all of us did come,</l>
                     <l>Where we ſhall bend our actions and to whom,</l>
                     <l>Shall reunite, as formerly you read.</l>
                     <l>The Members, ſo, divided from the Head</l>
                     <l>Shall move our Soveraign for to ſmile again,</l>
                     <l>And with his Subjects joyfully remain:</l>
                     <l>Shall ſtill be thought immediately the cauſe</l>
                     <l>Next unto God, that we poſſeſſe our Laws.</l>
                     <l>It ſhall ſpeak peace aſſuredly, and ſhall</l>
                     <l>Cure theſe diſeaſes Epidemicall;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:20"/>Shall make theſe Nations, happie, more and more,</l>
                     <l>And thrice ſo fruitfull, as they were before.</l>
                     <l>Shall make them quite forget the evils gone,</l>
                     <l>When they ſhall ſee their Soveraign in his throne.</l>
                     <l>O what a change then ſhall our ſouls perceive,</l>
                     <l>What greater pleaſure, could we wiſh or craue?</l>
                     <l>But all our former tears for to be wip'd</l>
                     <l>Away, and we, who were extremly ſtrip'd,</l>
                     <l>Shall be made glad: and all our by-paſt grief</l>
                     <l>Be turn'd from terror, to a full relief!</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall we ſing the praiſes of the day,</l>
                     <l>Wherein we heard the Proclamation ſay,</l>
                     <l>So many thouſands ſacrificed were,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall acknowledge, we be happier</l>
                     <l>By far, then ever we did think to be.</l>
                     <l>This is my hope, what ſay you now to me?</l>
                     <l>Or to my <hi>Muſe?</hi> is this not all you would?</l>
                     <l>Or what by me, was promiſt to be told?</l>
                     <l>Then let me yet, inſiſt a little ſtill,</l>
                     <l>And pen the praiſes, with my tyring quill</l>
                     <l>Of that moſt famous, glorious City, and</l>
                     <l>Set forth its fame; ſo making great the Land</l>
                     <l>Wherein it lies, fair <hi>London</hi> which hath lent</l>
                     <l>Its treaſure to afford us this content;</l>
                     <l>They ſpeak of <hi>Sparta,</hi> for its famous worth,</l>
                     <l>And write huge volumes for to ſet it forth:</l>
                     <l>The pens of <hi>Poets</hi> and their pains are ſpent</l>
                     <l>To praiſe its glory moſt magnificent:</l>
                     <l>Not onely for the grandor of its Gates,</l>
                     <l>Nor for thoſe vertues, which the world relates,</l>
                     <l>Nor for its pomp, nor for its pleaſant walls,</l>
                     <l>Nor for its Worthies, which within it dwels,</l>
                     <l>Nor for thoſe riches, which it doth contain,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet theſe Nobles, it doth entertain,</l>
                     <l>Nor for thoſe Statues, therein which do ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet the Archyes, builded with the hand</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:20"/>Of Curious art, nor for its ſtreets ſo fine,</l>
                     <l>Nor for ſuch things as they account divine:</l>
                     <l>Nor for the pleaſures of its breadth, nor length,</l>
                     <l>Nor for the numbers, which affords it ſtrength;</l>
                     <l>Nor for its fame, nor for its fair renown,</l>
                     <l>Nor all the things, that can extoll a Town:</l>
                     <l>But for a Cauſe, that cannot be expreſt,</l>
                     <l>And that is this, it far exceeds the reſt.</l>
                     <l>Yet all is nothing, if I ſhall compare</l>
                     <l>This Soveraign City in its vertues rare;</l>
                     <l>It far excels my telling, or my tongue,</l>
                     <l>My enterpriſes may provoke its wrong.</l>
                     <l>The pens of <hi>Poets,</hi> have been all imployd,</l>
                     <l>And all the <hi>Muſes,</hi> have their skill convoyd</l>
                     <l>To praiſe its pomp, its pleaſures to expreſſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſing the praiſes of its worthineſſe.</l>
                     <l>Its riches, and its Nobles doth exceed</l>
                     <l>Not onely <hi>Sparta,</hi> but all parts I read:</l>
                     <l>Its ſtatues are eſtabliſhed in ſtate,</l>
                     <l>With brave triumphant Archies on each gate:</l>
                     <l>Its ſtreets in ſtraightneſſe, ſtandeth as a line,</l>
                     <l>Pav'd ſo for pleaſure, it doth purely ſhine.</l>
                     <l>It is ſo ſpatious, yet of precious ſtones,</l>
                     <l>That every place, appeareth ſumptuous thrones,</l>
                     <l>It is the Seat of all Divinitie,</l>
                     <l>And in its Learning none can come it nigh.</l>
                     <l>A place ſo praiſt, and ſpoken of, a farre,</l>
                     <l>In juſt compare, no places equall are.</l>
                     <l>Are not the eyes of all the earth abroad</l>
                     <l>Fix'd on its glory, as it were a god?</l>
                     <l>Do not all Nations labour to reſide</l>
                     <l>Within this City? which can fully feed</l>
                     <l>Far more in number, with its raireſt dainty,</l>
                     <l>Then it can harbour, ſo great is its plenty:</l>
                     <l>A place wherein, all Nations are concern'd,</l>
                     <l>So populous, and yet ſo well govern'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:21"/>Beſides all theſe, in mornings of the Spring,</l>
                     <l>When Ecchoes anſwer, Quiriſters that ſing;</l>
                     <l>And from the ſteeples, when they ſtrain the Bells,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe melody ſweet Muſick paralels:</l>
                     <l>When all the airie branches of the trees</l>
                     <l>Are whiſtling for the multitudes of Bees:</l>
                     <l>And at whoſe wals, the Ocean once a day,</l>
                     <l>Or twice, or thrice, returns without delay,</l>
                     <l>To do it honour, and to waſh its walls;</l>
                     <l>Which having done, as ſurfeted it falls</l>
                     <l>Abake, for to imbrace its former banks,</l>
                     <l>And then returns, unto its by-paſt pranks.</l>
                     <l>That faireſt River of Renowned Fame,</l>
                     <l>Or Chryſtall Conduict, named by the <hi>Thame,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Almoſt ſurroundeth, this, ſo ſacred Citie,</l>
                     <l>That to compare with <hi>Sparta</hi> were a pitie.</l>
                     <l>And then we ſpeak of <hi>Sparta,</hi> by report,</l>
                     <l>So that ſuch contemplations, muſt come ſhort</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a thing as herein I intend,</l>
                     <l>Although I can the full not comprehend.</l>
                     <l>Yet in compare, I muſt expreſſe ſo much</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Lacedemons</hi> never dwelt in ſuch;</l>
                     <l>Not onely for all other things, but then</l>
                     <l>It far exceeds all Cities for the men:</l>
                     <l>Nor is this all yet, one thing I muſt tell,</l>
                     <l>In which fair <hi>London,</hi> doth the world excell,</l>
                     <l>And which indeed, makes all things to appear</l>
                     <l>The more delightfull, unto all that's here.</l>
                     <l>And of it ſelf the onely joy to men,</l>
                     <l>Superlative for pleaſure now and then:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe fair Idaeas, of the femall kind,</l>
                     <l>Such matchleſſe beauties no where ever ſhin'd;</l>
                     <l>The daintie viſage fair <hi>Venetian</hi> Dames,</l>
                     <l>Are far inferiour darkned at our flames</l>
                     <l>Of admir'd features; thoſe heart-piercing eyes,</l>
                     <l>In full reſemblance of the Deities.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:21"/>But Ile forbeare, I know their Sex are ſuch</l>
                     <l>They may wax prouder, if extold too much:</l>
                     <l>O fair magnifique glorious Citie thou</l>
                     <l>Art ſo exalted and extolled too</l>
                     <l>That my ſo ſhallow ſuperficiall brain</l>
                     <l>Cannot expreſſe (with ſuch a fluent ſtrain,</l>
                     <l>As is requir'd the excellencies and</l>
                     <l>The manner, method, form, how thou doſt ſtaud,</l>
                     <l>Upon the Eaſt part, where fair <hi>Phoebus</hi> riſe</l>
                     <l>There ſtands a Tower, with Crownes up to the skies</l>
                     <l>So ſtrong, ſo ſtately, each way wal'd about,</l>
                     <l>Such wealth within it, Lyons are without;</l>
                     <l>The famous <hi>Theams,</hi> which it doth ſtand upon</l>
                     <l>So arched over with a Chryſtall Throne,</l>
                     <l>That look afarre, and it appeareth there,</l>
                     <l>The Houſes hang, between the earth and aire:</l>
                     <l>And at the weſt, or other end of it,</l>
                     <l>Two palaces, where mighty Princes ſit,</l>
                     <l>Thereby the Stately monuments of Kings,</l>
                     <l>(Bedeck'd with robes, with Trophees, and ſuch things,</l>
                     <l>As ſhall remaine for glory of the place</l>
                     <l>Untill the time, that time ſhall have no race,)</l>
                     <l>doth ſtand, and with it, is adjoyn'd ſo nigh</l>
                     <l>As if it were it ſelfe, a Sanctuary,</l>
                     <l>A place appointed for a ſolemne ſeat</l>
                     <l>Where Orthodox divinity doth meet,</l>
                     <l>Between which two, the Tower and Royall Seat,</l>
                     <l>Such famous Churches ſtand in every ſtreet,</l>
                     <l>That if I erre not almoſt doth appear,</l>
                     <l>A ſeverall Church, for each day in the year:</l>
                     <l>There is the place eſtabliſh't for a throne</l>
                     <l>For Englands Soveraign's for to ſit upon,</l>
                     <l>There are the Seats of Juſtice for the Land,</l>
                     <l>And there the Scepter ſwayes in Juſtice hand,</l>
                     <l>There ſits the Counſel of that Court ſo high,</l>
                     <l>Which repreſents, a Royall Majeſty;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:22"/>That every thing; conſidered, as you ſee</l>
                     <l>It no more Citie, but a World may bee,</l>
                     <l>But ſtay my muſe, where minds thou for to run?</l>
                     <l>Haſt' not forgot thy ſelf, ſince thou begun?</l>
                     <l>Thou may'ſt run out in hyperbolick ſpeeches,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis much higher then thy knowledge reaches,</l>
                     <l>Forbeare with fairneſſe, labour not too far</l>
                     <l>Be not too forward runing in the warre,</l>
                     <l>Thou mayeſt looſe thy labour and abuſe</l>
                     <l>The good intentions of thy vertuous Muſe:</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt not ſeem too curious, nor too nice,</l>
                     <l>Let it ſuffice, that thou haſt broke the Ice;</l>
                     <l>It is the mark of any wiſe Commander</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a field, not too farre to wander,</l>
                     <l>The times are dangerous, and thou walk'ſt alone</l>
                     <l>And haſt to doe with more men then with one<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The number's many, which thou haſt to pleaſe</l>
                     <l>And thou art object of as many eyes:</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt run over in few certain hours</l>
                     <l>The Compaſſe of three Kingdomes, and their powers,</l>
                     <l>Haſt been in all the Armies of the land</l>
                     <l>With nothing but a pen into thy hand,</l>
                     <l>Haſt travel'd raſhly, and haſt met with many,</l>
                     <l>I think it ſtrange thou didſt not ſtrive with any,</l>
                     <l>But yet retire, remember I have told thee</l>
                     <l>A hundred thouſand thouſands may behold thee,</l>
                     <l>And of them all, perchance ſome may commend it,</l>
                     <l>And it may happen ſome men be offended.</l>
                     <l>But ſend it forth unto the world to view</l>
                     <l>Crave good men mercy, bid the bad adue.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="anagram">
                     <lg>
                        <head>William Mercer. Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I arm merci well.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I arm merci well, arm's and merci too,</l>
                        <l>I here expreſſe, and leavs the reſt to you.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <div type="title_page">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:22"/>
                     <p>Angliae Speculum: OR ENGLANDS LOOKING-GLASSE.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Part, Conſiſting of ſeverall <hi>Speeches, Anagrams, Epigrams, Acroſticks,</hi> and <hi>Sonnets.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>By C. VV. MERCER.</p>
                     <q>Scribimus indocti, doctique poaemata paſsim.</q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho: Paine.</hi> MDCXLVI.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:23"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:23"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable LORDS Aſſembled in <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>SHall duſt and aſhes dare to utter words</l>
                     <l>In preſence of ſuch high &amp; mighty Lords?</l>
                     <l>Who are ſo ſet, and circled by the throne</l>
                     <l>Which their dread ſoveraign uſe to ſit upon:</l>
                     <l>Dare I lift up my eyes upon that place?</l>
                     <l>Or ſhall I have the honour to imbrace</l>
                     <l>Time for to talk? or will they tell me, I</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtand aſide, they are a Majeſty;</l>
                     <l>Made up of many: no, no, not ſo, they</l>
                     <l>Are not ſo proud, their preſence every day</l>
                     <l>They do afford; therefore let me not fail</l>
                     <l>To enterpriſe, my purpoſe will prevail:</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I think of ſuch things as forbearing?</l>
                     <l>The tale is ill that is not worth the hearing.</l>
                     <l>Thoſe noble Lords are Peers into the Land</l>
                     <l>Brooks not ſuch pride: I pray you underſtand,</l>
                     <l>They are the chief, moſt eminent, allow'd,</l>
                     <l>For Englands vertues; will you have them proud?</l>
                     <l>No, I perſwade you, will you walk about,</l>
                     <l>And view the world, even every way throughout:</l>
                     <l>Scarce ſhall you find ſuch Worthies as they are,</l>
                     <l>Or ſuch as can compare with them, by far<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in purſuance what you hear me ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>Come but and liſten, you ſhall ſee me ſeek.</l>
                     <l>And crave their patience, and make bold to ask,</l>
                     <l>And in their preſence will preſent my task.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:24"/>Moſt noble Lords, whoſe conſtanci's admird<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whoſe Vertues waies, and travels are untyrd;</l>
                     <l>By whoſe conſent, the Scepter beareth ſway,</l>
                     <l>And in your great aſſembly every day.</l>
                     <l>What conſtant minds, are ſeen about your throne;</l>
                     <l>What noble Spirits do appeare thereon,</l>
                     <l>What joyfull ſmiles, ſhine in the ſubjects ey,</l>
                     <l>To ſee amongſt you, ſuch a Sympathy;</l>
                     <l>No emulation, nor confounding pride,</l>
                     <l>Your high attempts, nor actions doth divide,</l>
                     <l>Your enterpriſes are ſo prudent ſtill,</l>
                     <l>You nothing but, the ancient lawes fullfill,</l>
                     <l>You ſtill concurre, and with the Commons ſtand</l>
                     <l>Their Honours thereby, beare an equall hand,</l>
                     <l>What high applaus ſhall be pronounc'd of you,</l>
                     <l>When after ages, ſhall repeat your due?</l>
                     <l>Declaring how you ſtayed with the State</l>
                     <l>When there was ſtriving dayly in debate:</l>
                     <l>Some going hence and others doubting what</l>
                     <l>Was beſt to do, yet you not queſtion'd that;</l>
                     <l>Did not my brave and Noble <hi>ESSEX</hi> ever</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt all Temptations conſtantly perſever?</l>
                     <l>What ſhall be ſaid for all your certain waies?</l>
                     <l>Your Noble brow's, ſhall beare a crown of <hi>boyes:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thus if I fail in what my muſe affords,</l>
                     <l>I humbly leave it to the Houſe of Lords.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:24"/>
                     <head>To the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</head>
                     <l>VVHere am I now? O! let me wiſely weigh</l>
                     <l>Since I preſume thus, to approach ſo high;</l>
                     <l>As to appeare in preſence of that place</l>
                     <l>Which is ſo ſtor'd with ſtatelineſſe, and grace,</l>
                     <l>The body which doth repreſent a King,</l>
                     <l>Admits no title but a Sacred thing,</l>
                     <l>Each member there, may well be ſaid to be</l>
                     <l>A perfect part of our chiefe Sanctuarie:</l>
                     <l>The true extract of Wiſdom, and the beſt</l>
                     <l>Which by conſent, are ſifted from the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe eaſleſſe labours, with impartiall eyes,</l>
                     <l>Prevents the dangers, dayly which ariſe,</l>
                     <l>Expires their Spirits, almoſt to regaine</l>
                     <l>What curſed catives, labours for in vaine,</l>
                     <l>Are early up, can skarcely go to bed,</l>
                     <l>Five falls and ſprings, ſuch troubles have they had,</l>
                     <l>Muſt heare the cries, of every one that are</l>
                     <l>Almoſt confounded with this cruel war.</l>
                     <l>The great man coms, petitions in his griefe;</l>
                     <l>And then the poor petitions for reliefe:</l>
                     <l>The Widdow cryes, my husband's ſlain, and I</l>
                     <l>Am deſtitute for want of food may dy.</l>
                     <l>Then comes the Orphan, Loudly cries alaſſe</l>
                     <l>I moſt of all am in a fearfull caſe:</l>
                     <l>As alſo numbers of the hurt, and lame,</l>
                     <l>All have recourſe, calls for reliefe at them:</l>
                     <l>The great and mean, the deſtitute and poore,</l>
                     <l>All call for pittie at their pious doore.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:25"/>Yet they have patience, and do much prevent</l>
                     <l>The preſſing ſorrowes of the diſcontent:</l>
                     <l>Like to the tender parents, who provide</l>
                     <l>For ſuch, as on them faithfully confide:</l>
                     <l>Themſelves are robd of all that was their own,</l>
                     <l>Yet muſt maintain ſuch as are overthrown.</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtrive to ſtill the out-cryes of all thoſe</l>
                     <l>Who have been ruind by their raging foes:</l>
                     <l>But wherewith do they what they have to do?</l>
                     <l>I ask it of thee, and muſt tell thee too:</l>
                     <l>Their prudence, and unwearied pains appear,</l>
                     <l>They do provide it, though it be not here:</l>
                     <l>Their ardent prayers prevaileth moſt of all:</l>
                     <l>God grants their ſuits, they ſo divinely call;</l>
                     <l>See how they do ſuch certain dayes allot</l>
                     <l>For ſuch occaſions as requireth note:</l>
                     <l>Each moneth a ſolemn publick <hi>Faſt</hi> they keep,</l>
                     <l>Preſents their pray'rs in private, and they weep:</l>
                     <l>What they forbear, that is collected truly,</l>
                     <l>And to the poor is dedicated duly:</l>
                     <l>They put reſtraint long ſince to ſinfull plaies,</l>
                     <l>And have prevented idle holy-daies:</l>
                     <l>They have collections conſtant for the needy:</l>
                     <l>To act ſuch things, their goodnes makes them greedy:</l>
                     <l>'Tis not the heat of Summers ſcorching Sun,</l>
                     <l>Makes them deſert the buſines begun:</l>
                     <l>Nor yet the ſharpnes of the winters day,</l>
                     <l>Prevents their travels, nor provokes delay:</l>
                     <l>But they go on ſtill, with undaunted fear;</l>
                     <l>Obſerves no times, nor ſeaſons of the year.</l>
                     <l>This is the courſe continually they keep,</l>
                     <l>More conſtant then they either eat, or ſleep:</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:25"/>Yet all is counted nothing, ſince they can</l>
                     <l>Not pleaſe the perſons of each private man;</l>
                     <l>This is the thanks they conquiſh for their care,</l>
                     <l>They boldly ask them, wherefore ſit they there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But O! the charge wherein they are ingag'd,</l>
                     <l>Cals for our reverence not to be enrag'd;</l>
                     <l>But theſe are they, thoſe Worthies whom I would</l>
                     <l>If I had knowledge, faithfully unfold;</l>
                     <l>But ſince my skill cannot extend ſo high,</l>
                     <l>I muſt deſiſt, and pardon of them cry:</l>
                     <l>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> actions are true witneſſe of their wayes,</l>
                     <l>What ever malice, or <hi>Malignants</hi> ſayes.</l>
                     <l>And in the Evening of their wearied day</l>
                     <l>Their greateſt foes, ſhall be enforc'd to ſay,</l>
                     <l>They have done well; and in the end of all</l>
                     <l>For their rewards, receive a welcome ſhall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>So that at laſt, they ſhall be cald to riſe,</l>
                     <l>And keep their Meeting farre above the skies.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:26"/>
                     <head>TO The Right Honourable the LORDS COMMISSIONERS of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>MY LORDS,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <l>AS you are perſons of a High diſcent,</l>
                     <l>So do your perſons highly repreſent,</l>
                     <l>The body of a Kingdomes whole eſtate,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe former freedomes, need I not relate;</l>
                     <l>You know the caſe, therefore I will forbear,</l>
                     <l>Yet let me humbly tell you ſince ye're here,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Scotland</hi> hath kepe its Crown unconquiſh'd ever,</l>
                     <l>Foes oft invaded, but they had it never;</l>
                     <l>Nor did they love it for its riches then,</l>
                     <l>But for the active ſpirits of the men:</l>
                     <l>By whoſe aſſiſtance, all the world ſo wide,</l>
                     <l>So much triumphs; and in their faith confide.</l>
                     <l>How great a Glory is it to that place?</l>
                     <l>They had the honour in ſo ſhort a ſpace,</l>
                     <l>Even by their pow'r, to enter and withſtand</l>
                     <l>The ſorrowes threatned in their Neighbours Land;</l>
                     <l>By their aſſiſtance ſet the Borders free,</l>
                     <l>And what they did, the world a witneſſe be?</l>
                     <l>This is the Land, theſe are the men, for who,</l>
                     <l>You all were choſen, and came here to do:</l>
                     <l>Be not too ſlow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor ſeem not in a fleep,</l>
                     <l>Loſe not the thing, which you ſo long did keep;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:26"/>Caſt not your burthen, on this noble Band,</l>
                     <l>But know your ſelves beſt what you have in hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>They have affairs ſo weighty, that they muſt</l>
                     <l>Begin at home, according to their Truſt;</l>
                     <l>Think on your ſelves, and that, for which you came,</l>
                     <l>It is enough, all is allow'd by them:</l>
                     <l>Nor onely muſt the Publike be relieved,</l>
                     <l>But every private Member that is grieved,</l>
                     <l>It doth belong a little to your charge,</l>
                     <l>Such to aſſiſt; or if you doe inlarge</l>
                     <l>Your warrant there, it cannot do amiſſe:</l>
                     <l>You may commit a greater ſinne then this,</l>
                     <l>And I conceive it cannot give offence</l>
                     <l>To further things that ſuffer in ſuſpence,</l>
                     <l>Such as were ſharers in the ſelf-ſame thing</l>
                     <l>For w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ich you ſay, you did your Army bring,</l>
                     <l>And Natives too, it cannot be unfit,</l>
                     <l>For to befriend them, they deſerved it,</l>
                     <l>In Suits ſo juſt, what is't you may not do?</l>
                     <l>They covenanted for to anſwer you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then your actions cannot but muſt thrive</l>
                     <l>Such grave Divines, aſſiſt you to contrive,</l>
                     <l>Who conſtantly invoke with holy words,</l>
                     <l>For bleſſings from above, and ſo affords</l>
                     <l>Aſſiſtance alway's, from the heavenly Throne,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill obtains the ſame before they'r gone.</l>
                     <l>Then in a three-fold manner may you take,</l>
                     <l>Concurrence alſo, and a Linck may make,</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch-like ſtrength, as it will ever laſt</l>
                     <l>For to prevail, and take it from the reſt,</l>
                     <l>I meane of thoſe judicions Gentlemen,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Ayd you have, and I am certain then,</l>
                     <l>You nothing can deſire, not yet demand</l>
                     <l>But you will ſurely have it at their hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Excuſe my boldneſſe, that I ſpeak ſo much,</l>
                     <l>But I preſume becauſe I know you ſuch</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:27"/>You will but ſmile, to ſee a ſouldiers Pen</l>
                     <l>Imployd to write, unto ſuch mighty men;</l>
                     <l>But to be plain, I am ſo poor in purſe</l>
                     <l>And void of learning; which the greater curſe?</l>
                     <l>That I conſider, neither what I ſay,</l>
                     <l>Nor what I write, nor have I time to ſtay:</l>
                     <l>Yet Noble Lords, the errors that I make</l>
                     <l>I pray you pardon, for the Countries ſake.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <head>TO <hi>THE HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> COMMITTEES.</head>
                     <l>COmmittee-men, ſo cald, no queſtion then;</l>
                     <l>It were moſt needfull you were honeſt men:</l>
                     <l>For by the name Committee, you may finde,</l>
                     <l>All is committed to your honeſt minde.</l>
                     <l>Abuſe not then what comes into your truſt,</l>
                     <l>Committee-men ſhould conſtantly be juſt;</l>
                     <l>Know you are Members of that Noble place,</l>
                     <l>Which pleads its pow'r proceeds of Law, and Grace.</l>
                     <l>You all are ſworn to be juſt, and then,</l>
                     <l>If yee be ſo, ye'r right Committee-men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I do believe ye all are juſt, but ye,</l>
                     <l>Muſt not believe me, not unleſſe ye be</l>
                     <l>Both juſt, and honeſt, and you muſt examine</l>
                     <l>Your ſelves in ſecret, what concerns the ſamen;</l>
                     <l>Stain not that State from whence you do proceed,</l>
                     <l>Shun long debate, in things concerning need.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:27"/>You men of honour, think upon your fame</l>
                     <l>Be not defil'd, it is a fearfull ſhame:</l>
                     <l>And you who are men of a meaner kinde</l>
                     <l>Be not perſwaded to a partiall minde;</l>
                     <l>Nor let not love, nor hatred, nor the luſt</l>
                     <l>Of earthly things, move thee to be unjuſt;</l>
                     <l>Nor waxe too proud, becauſe thou ſees thou can,</l>
                     <l>Sit in the Chair as chief Committee-man:</l>
                     <l>But now I fear, that thou wilt ſhake thy head,</l>
                     <l>And think me ſawcie, for the thing ye read,</l>
                     <l>Yet I have had experience now and then</l>
                     <l>Of ſome of thoſe you call Committee-men,</l>
                     <l>And if you chide or challenge me, in ſpite,</l>
                     <l>I will accompt you, one of whom I write;</l>
                     <l>Beſides, conceive the nature of the time,</l>
                     <l>And you will give me leave to ſpeak in rime:</l>
                     <l>Or if you quarrell, and will call me to it</l>
                     <l>And queſtion me, how I durſt dare to do it?</l>
                     <l>I tell you this, the wats have made me bold,</l>
                     <l>And I am lately, very ſcarce of gold;</l>
                     <l>That to be plain, I have no more to ſay,</l>
                     <l>But cure this evill,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall humbly pray.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:28"/>
                     <head>TO The Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Northumberland:</hi> Earl ALGERNOUNE PERCIE.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Areall Princel'e Governer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>A reall Princely Governour, <hi>ſo be;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy royall Name denotes ſo much to me.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>TO thee brave <hi>Piercy,</hi> in thy prime of yeers,</l>
                        <l>Who art made choiſe of 'mongſt the chiefeſt Peers,</l>
                        <l>To be great Guardian for the good of them,</l>
                        <l>The royall Off-ſprings. of a Diadem.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe hopefull branches of that high-born Stock,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe Infant-Anchors, <hi>Englands</hi> fenced Rock,</l>
                        <l>The rareſt fruit, which heretofore have ſprung,</l>
                        <l>Apparent heyrs to Kingdomes, though they'r young:</l>
                        <l>How grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> truſt then, is repos'd in thee,</l>
                        <l>To have ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Treaſures in thy cuſtody?</l>
                        <l>But ſure, experience of thy by-paſt worth,</l>
                        <l>Hath thee promoted, and haſte pointed forth</l>
                        <l>Thee onely fit; for ſuch brave, high deſignes,</l>
                        <l>The education of ſuch Princely Vines.</l>
                        <l>Long may they live, and riſe to honours high,</l>
                        <l>Even till each one become a Majeſty.</l>
                        <l>And thou, great Earl, whoſe Grandor ſhines in ſtate,</l>
                        <l>Live ſtill in ſpight of deſtiny, and fate.</l>
                        <l>I know not whether of thy parts to praiſe;</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf, place, fame, thou equall art in theſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:28"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable the Earl of PEMBROOK: Earle PHILLIP HERBERT.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Peer help al liberty.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Peer help all liberty; <hi>Brave Lord, we ſee</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy actions, and thy Anagram agree.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>REnowned Lord, brave Earl, fair <hi>Englands</hi> pride,</l>
                        <l>I ſtile thee ſo, ſince <hi>England</hi> doth conſide,</l>
                        <l>And ever did, in thy fidelity,</l>
                        <l>Both in their triumphs and tranquilitie.</l>
                        <l>Firſt, while this Nation did ſecurely reſt,</l>
                        <l>As thou waſt Noble thou wert worthieſt:</l>
                        <l>For ſtill the Court, thy carriage did commend</l>
                        <l>Didſt not co-act for thy luxurious end:</l>
                        <l>And now when <hi>Mars</hi> did muſter all at armes,</l>
                        <l>Thou ſtill art conſtant upon equall termes.</l>
                        <l>True to the State, couragious in faith,</l>
                        <l>Moſt abſolute in minde unto the death.</l>
                        <l>A rare example in a caſe ſo high,</l>
                        <l>Friend both to ſubject and His Majeſtie.</l>
                        <l>The Tombs of Traitours, where their Herſesare,</l>
                        <l>Shall all bear witneſſe, how wiſe <hi>Pembrook,</hi> farre</l>
                        <l>Surpaſs'd their practice; and his Trophées ſhall</l>
                        <l>Survive in honour, when theirs, periſh all,</l>
                        <l>Patron of truth, patern in Pietie,</l>
                        <l>Two matchleſſe Emblems, of Nobilitie,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pembrook</hi> for Prudence, Piety, and worth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Theſe Epethites ſhall onely ſet thee forth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:29"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable Earl, Lord <hi>WILLIAM CECIL</hi> of SALISBURY.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anag.</head>
                        <l>I Will really accord.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Agree in truth,</hi> I will really accord,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To nothing elſe, Will I conſent afford.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>SO high a <hi>Task,</hi> to undertake or chuſe,</l>
                        <l>For my ſo empty <hi>brdin,</hi> or ſhallow <hi>Muſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Doth argue <hi>Weakneſſe,</hi> for it is a thing,</l>
                        <l>My knowledge cannot; to <hi>perfection</hi> bring.</l>
                        <l>Yet in ſubmiſſion, from a loyall <hi>heart,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I undertake <hi>ſincerely</hi> to impart,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe high extended <hi>excellencies,</hi> rare,</l>
                        <l>Which with the beſt; moſt worthy may compare:</l>
                        <l>A high-born, <hi>Baron,</hi> ancient <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>Earl,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of matchleſſe <hi>ſplendor,</hi> bright as any <hi>Pearl,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>True <hi>Conquerour</hi> of <hi>Honour, Valour,</hi> fame,</l>
                        <l>Of vertue, favour, and magnifick name!</l>
                        <l>So Conſtant, in, the cauſe for which we fight,</l>
                        <l>And ſpend our bloud, maintaining <hi>Englands</hi> right.</l>
                        <l>Adds thy aſſiſting Land, unto tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e Lords,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe matchleſſe wiſedome, all true worth affords.</l>
                        <l>Of thee therefore, whoſe Vertues are ſo high,</l>
                        <l>I take my leave; in all humility.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:29"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable the Earl of Warwick, Lord High-Admirall of <hi>England. Earle</hi> ROBERT RICH.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anag.</head>
                        <l>Thrice real, or beter.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Warwicks Heroick,</hi> Thrice reall, or better,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Brave Admirall, all</hi> England <hi>is thy debtor.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THis new: prepared piece, though it be dumb,</l>
                        <l>Yet repreſents, as it is <hi>Speculum,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The chiefeſt Actors, in this Great debate,</l>
                        <l>Between the Sovereign, and this Mighty State.</l>
                        <l>I am not ty'd, nor muſt I, ſtand content,</l>
                        <l>Howbe't it be without my Element.</l>
                        <l>But ſince your honour had the ſole command</l>
                        <l>By Sea, and guarded us upon the Land;</l>
                        <l>Where, when your greatneſſe did on <hi>Neptune</hi> ride,</l>
                        <l>And notwithſtanding of his ſwelling pride,</l>
                        <l>Triumphed there; mongſt his frothy flouds,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe threatnings ſeem'd to ſwallow up the Clouds.</l>
                        <l>Yet there you rul'd, and forced forraign pow'rs,</l>
                        <l>For to forbear, theſe Iſlands here of ours.</l>
                        <l>Wherefore while I, thoſe Worthies do proclaim,</l>
                        <l>I muſt make bold, to magnifie your fame;</l>
                        <l>Whoſe admir'd warfares, and Heroick deeds,</l>
                        <l>Shall be recorded unto all that reads:</l>
                        <l>That your affection to your Native Land,</l>
                        <l>May be perceived, though by the Seas command:</l>
                        <l>Brave <hi>Warwicks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> Valour ſhall be ſtated ſtill,</l>
                        <l>Till <hi>Neptune</hi> no more ſhall be ſeen to fiil,</l>
                        <l>Daign yet the greatneſſe of your dignity,</l>
                        <l>Accept this ſigne, of my humility.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:30"/>
                     <head>TO <hi>The Right Honourable</hi> Bazill Fielding, Earl Denbeigh.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Fli'd il, begin zeal.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I fli'd from ill, in <hi>zeal I did begin,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In all my acts, continued ſtill therein.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>BRave Lord thy Banners in this War were born,</l>
                        <l>And were by <hi>Mars</hi> both maſſacred, and torn,</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf bore Arms, when errours thought to rage,</l>
                        <l>And act'd thy part, upon that Tragick Stage:</l>
                        <l>Where dead mens ſculs, lay ſtrowed on the ground,</l>
                        <l>A ſunder from their bodyes being found.</l>
                        <l>There thou triumph'd, againſt their tyrannie,</l>
                        <l>And rais'd up Trophees of thy Victory.</l>
                        <l>Prov'd active, faithfull, valourous and juſt,</l>
                        <l>And no leſſe conſtant, in continuall truſt.</l>
                        <l>Expos'd thy perſon, and didſt ſpend thy ſtate,</l>
                        <l>Incur'd the danger of thy Soveraignes hate;</l>
                        <l>Art one in number of the Houſe of Lords,</l>
                        <l>So all theſe reaſons, matter me affords,</l>
                        <l>To fall upon this ſubject, and to pen,</l>
                        <l>Thy praiſe; and place thee with thoſe Noble men.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:30"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Earle Henerie Rich.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Here hence ir' realj<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Here hence ire really. <hi>Thy Eagle-ſoring Wings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Surmounts all envy,</hi> Ire, <hi>or ſuch like things.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>WHat high Renown can be return'd by me,</l>
                        <l>Moſt Noble Lord, as attributes to thee?</l>
                        <l>Extents of honours, in their rareſt kinde,</l>
                        <l>On <hi>Hollands</hi> head have been increas'd I finde:</l>
                        <l>Bounty beyond expreſſions of my Pen,</l>
                        <l>Thy beauty too, exceeds the Sex of men;</l>
                        <l>The miracle of Fame, <hi>Dame</hi> Natures glore,</l>
                        <l>The life of vertue, graces houſe of ſtore:</l>
                        <l>Thy Courtly preſence, and thy Princely grace,</l>
                        <l>Adds to the ſplendor of thy Royall Race.</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Spain,</hi> nor <hi>France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> nor all,</l>
                        <l>The Nations, nam'd; on this unmeaſured Ball,</l>
                        <l>Can juſtly brag of ſuch a one in worth,</l>
                        <l>For valour, vertue, and what iſſues forth.</l>
                        <l>The rareſt tongue of Eloquence, and skill,</l>
                        <l>Which doth exceed, brave <hi>Cicero</hi> his quill.</l>
                        <l>The mindes of Monarchs, and the Courts of Kings,</l>
                        <l>Are onely fit, for ſuch unequald things.</l>
                        <l>The eyes of <hi>England,</hi> gloried heretofore,</l>
                        <l>In thee brave <hi>Holland,</hi> pray thee keep thy ſtore,</l>
                        <l>And ſtand aſide, leſt any ſtain thy ſtate,</l>
                        <l>By private Envie, undeſerved hate.</l>
                        <l>And when thou find'ſt occaſion, then come on,</l>
                        <l>Thy perſon fits, for to approach a Throne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:31"/>
                     <head>To the Right honourable the E. of Mancheſter, <hi>Earl Edward Montigue.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Do not gr'eve me, I rul'd al.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Do not grieve me, I rul'd all; <hi>at arms,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Where I commanded, kept you all from harms.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THat priviledge which Poëts do preſume,</l>
                        <l>To practice by, I ſhall not need aſſume;</l>
                        <l>Theſe are but fictions, for to figure forth</l>
                        <l>Such counterfeits, as have no reall worth.</l>
                        <l>If I had <hi>Tullyes</hi> Eloquence of tongues,</l>
                        <l>And all the Nature to the Nine belongs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Or rare <hi>Apelles</hi> knowledge in his Art,</l>
                        <l>And ſhould imploy them all, for to impart,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe Noble vertues, valourous and wiſe,</l>
                        <l>Heroique actions, which do ſympathize,</l>
                        <l>And correſpond with theſe brave Worthies here,</l>
                        <l>They could not yet ſo exquiſite appear,</l>
                        <l>For to demonſtrate, nor draw to the life,</l>
                        <l>Thy high deſervings, but engender ſtrife;</l>
                        <l>And there ſhould ſtay; and not determine truly,</l>
                        <l>The rich eſteem of thy demerits duly.</l>
                        <l>The Chronicles of <hi>Englands</hi> true record,</l>
                        <l>Shall eternize thy Noble name, brave Lord.</l>
                        <l>Time ſhall expire, but that extent ſhall not</l>
                        <l>Extenuate, nor thy remembrance rot;</l>
                        <l>Succeeding ages, while the ayr gives breath,</l>
                        <l>Shall ſpeak, how thou expos'd thy ſelf to death,</l>
                        <l>In doing ſervice for this famous Land,</l>
                        <l>Wherein thou art a Prince, Peer, Earl, and</l>
                        <l>Which yet is more then each of theſe, or all;</l>
                        <l>Next to brave <hi>Eſſex,</hi> ſecond Generall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:31"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>Henerie Gray,</hi> Earl of STANFORD.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Agree herein, realy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Forſake all</hi> Shichems, <hi>take conſent of me,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Maintain the truth,</hi> herein, really agree.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>MOſt <hi>courteous,</hi> and right ſtately <hi>Stanford,</hi> thou,</l>
                        <l>To whom I'm <hi>bent</hi> to pay that reall <hi>Vow,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which for thy <hi>worth,</hi> I ſolemnly have <hi>ſworn,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And in my <hi>breaſt,</hi> ſo long a time have born:</l>
                        <l>Becauſe thy conſtant <hi>countenance,</hi> hath ſtill</l>
                        <l>Been oppoſite, to <hi>Actors</hi> in this ill.</l>
                        <l>Haſt proved <hi>pious, pregnant, painfull,</hi> and</l>
                        <l>With reſolution, for the <hi>Faith</hi> didſt ſtand.</l>
                        <l>Sent forth the ſubſtance of thy ſelf, thy <hi>Sonne,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And free-born <hi>Heyr;</hi> what further could be done?</l>
                        <l>To fight in <hi>Battles</hi> for thy Native Land,</l>
                        <l>And for the Subjects <hi>freedome,</hi> for to ſtand.</l>
                        <l>Thus then thy ſelf, ſtill by <hi>unceſſant</hi> pains,</l>
                        <l>Untill this time <hi>untyr'd,</hi> and <hi>true</hi> remains,</l>
                        <l>To ſerve the <hi>State;</hi> and as I ſaid, even ſo</l>
                        <l>Thy Noble Son, as <hi>reſolute</hi> didſt go;</l>
                        <l>And made a two-fold tye, to truth and fame,</l>
                        <l>In lines of Gold to write thy worthy Name.</l>
                        <l>And yet another reaſon moves me too,</l>
                        <l>In humble thanks to do this that I do.</l>
                        <l>Thou art a lover of that Native Land,</l>
                        <l>From whence I came; and who for <hi>England</hi> ſtand.</l>
                        <l>All theſe, and I, ſhall ſtill be bound to ſay,</l>
                        <l>Live ſtill in honour, ſtately <hi>Stanford, Gray.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:32"/>
                     <head>TO <hi>The Right Honourable</hi> John Maitland, Earl of Lauderſdale: <hi>Earle John Maitland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I aim'd at reall honer.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I aim'd at reall honour; <hi>that, I will afford:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To leſſe then that, I never will accord.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>ONe conſtant Star, ſtill in the North did ſtand,</l>
                        <l>A Directory both by Sea, and Land:</l>
                        <l>But now two lights, more glorious then that one,</l>
                        <l>Are ſeen appear, forth from that Horizone.</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhineſt for one, brave <hi>Lauderſdale,</hi> a Star,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe ſplendour bright ſurpaſſe all others far:</l>
                        <l>But being darkned by the Clouds at home,</l>
                        <l>Thou chang'd thy Seat, and to the South didſt come.</l>
                        <l>To let thy Light, ſhine conſtant, cleer, and pure,</l>
                        <l>Though wandring Stars, ſhall vaniſh, not endure.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:32"/>
                     <head>TO THE <hi>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE</hi> JOHN ELPHINGSTOWNE. Lord Balmerinoch.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I own honest helping.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I own honeſt helping, <hi>and I did engage,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>For honest help, the Covenant in plage.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>THat other light for which I lent my word,</l>
                        <l>Thou art; our wiſe <hi>Balmerinoch,</hi> brave Lord,</l>
                        <l>Who chang'd thy own true proper place in Sphear,</l>
                        <l>And ſet thy ſelf to ſhine in <hi>Englands</hi> ayr:</l>
                        <l>Shine ſtill, but ſo, that ſending beams abroad,</l>
                        <l>Thy light reflect upon thy old abode.</l>
                        <l>Seek <hi>Englands</hi> good, next thy Creators glory</l>
                        <l>In all thy actions, and thy Oratorie.</l>
                        <l>But having ſhin'd, and ſhew'd thy true intent,</l>
                        <l>Return, and ſhine in thy own Firmament.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:33"/>
                     <head>TO The Right Honourable <hi>William Fiennes,</hi> Viſcouut SAY and SEAL.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Live man, flee ſin.</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe in, live in fam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>.</l>
                        <l>Wiſe man in life.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Live man, flee ſin'; Uſe in, live in fame,</l>
                        <l>Wiſe man in life; <hi>Theſe are thy very Name.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>MEcoenas</hi> is made <hi>famous</hi> for his Wit,</l>
                        <l>Yet thine is not inferiour unto it,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mars</hi> by no name but <hi>Mars,</hi> can be made known,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Say</hi> (thy name) doth <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seal</hi> thine own.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Poëts</hi> ſpend time, and ſpeak in praiſe of <hi>Plato,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And ſhew the rare <hi>excellencies</hi> of <hi>Cato:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I, reading finde, <hi>Remembrances</hi> of ſome</l>
                        <l>So high <hi>extold;</hi> grave <hi>Senators</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But though it did, ſo brag, and boaſt, I dar'</l>
                        <l>Avouch, that <hi>London,</hi> may out-brag it far.</l>
                        <l>For neither <hi>Plato,</hi> for his wiſeſt parts,</l>
                        <l>Nor <hi>Mars</hi> for valour, <hi>Cato</hi> for his <hi>Arts,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor yet <hi>Mecoenas,</hi> for his worthy praiſe,</l>
                        <l>They need not make ſo much report of theſe.</l>
                        <l>Nor yet needs <hi>Rome,</hi> extoll, and tell ſo much,</l>
                        <l>As if the world, nor we, could ſhew them ſuch.</l>
                        <l>Againſt them all, I do proteſt, appeal,</l>
                        <l>To thee brave <hi>Fiennes,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Seal.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:33"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>William Gray,</hi> Lord GRAY.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Aym, I will agr'e.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What good I gather in your mindes to be,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Firſt, I will ſpeak, then,</hi> Aym, I will agr'e.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THoſe worthy Heroes, thrice Renowned Earles,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe luſtre ſhines, more bright then Orient Pearles,</l>
                        <l>Or as thoſe Stars, which gliſter in the ſphear,</l>
                        <l>When duskie darkneſſe, mantles o'er the ayr;</l>
                        <l>VVhen they brave Lord, in preſence of that place</l>
                        <l>Approach, with prudence, ſtatelineſſe, and grace,</l>
                        <l>They do make choiſe to charge thee, for thy worth,</l>
                        <l>To contribute thoſe ſecret thoughts, ſent forth;</l>
                        <l>From their ſo wiſe impartiall breaſts, they aym,</l>
                        <l>And thou a wiſe <hi>Mecoenas</hi> ſits with them,</l>
                        <l>And finding all their actions faithfull be,</l>
                        <l>Thou hear'ſt them ſpeak, then ſayes, <hi>I will agree.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To thee brave Lord, the Loadſtone of the State.</l>
                        <l>VVhoſe worth appears, in intricate debate,</l>
                        <l>Attractive, and, by underſtanding too,</l>
                        <l>Thou firſt collects, then wiſely doſt thou do.</l>
                        <l>Diſpenſing all in ſuch a pious way,</l>
                        <l>Pure in thy colour, conſtant, reall <hi>Gray.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The acts of England ſhall be clad with thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>And thy rich fame, thereby renowned be.</l>
                        <l>But worthy Lord, let me pertake of this,</l>
                        <l>Thy Noble word (though in Parentheſis)</l>
                        <l>And then return, into thy ſtate again,</l>
                        <l>In endleſſe honour, and I ſay Amen.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:34"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:35"/>
                     <head>TO The Right Honourable LORD IOHN ROBERTS: Lord ROBERTS of Truro.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Trie on bold Hero's.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Try on bold Hero's, <hi>do thou, nothing remove at,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In all attempts,</hi> Fortuna audaces juvat.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>HEroick <hi>Roberts,</hi> and renowned <hi>Lord,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>With <hi>Martiall</hi> actions, in aboundance ſtor'd,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe <hi>valour</hi> hath <hi>triumphantly</hi> trode down,</l>
                        <l>Brave <hi>Englands</hi> foes, with thy undaunted frown.</l>
                        <l>Thoſe feats of Warre which from thy force, did flye,</l>
                        <l>And ſeconded, ſo by thy <hi>piercing</hi> eye,</l>
                        <l>Did cruſh thy <hi>foes,</hi> and make them trembling ſtand,</l>
                        <l>By <hi>Manhood,</hi> and thy <hi>Method,</hi> in command.</l>
                        <l>Great <hi>Mars</hi> Field-Marſhall, when his <hi>Armies</hi> met,</l>
                        <l>Sole ſentence-giver, when his Conſuls ſet:</l>
                        <l>Thy worth, thy vertue, and <hi>unequal'd</hi> fame,</l>
                        <l>Are <hi>Epithites,</hi> but onely of thy Name;</l>
                        <l>Thy paſſive actions, pious, peremptory</l>
                        <l>Are reall <hi>Emblems</hi> of thy endleſſe glory.</l>
                        <l>What then although, I often was a witneſſe</l>
                        <l>Of thy exploits, yet muſt my Muſe's unfitneſſe</l>
                        <l>Forbear, and ceaſe; nor can ſhe ſolemnize,</l>
                        <l>Thy high deſervings in their juſt degrees.</l>
                        <l>Or why ſhould I, with this my fleeting quill,</l>
                        <l>Seek for to ſound thy praiſe? I do but ill.</l>
                        <l>Thy worth is written with thoſe drops of <hi>Blood,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which ſeals thy <hi>Honour</hi> for thy Countries good.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:35"/>
                     <head>TO the right Honourable <hi>Thomas Bruce,</hi> Lord BRUCE.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anag.</head>
                        <l>Com, be as tru'.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Come, be as true, <hi>unto your State as I.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who ſhall aſſiſt with all fidelity,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>I Stand obliged, by a ſtrong relation,</l>
                        <l>To pay thee tribute; one is from the Nation,</l>
                        <l>Whereof thou art, an ancient Earl true born,</l>
                        <l>And I a Native of the ſame am ſworn.</l>
                        <l>The ſecond cauſe, by which I finde me bound,</l>
                        <l>Is this; thy actions have been alwayes found</l>
                        <l>So faithfull here; in what thou doſt afford</l>
                        <l>For <hi>Englands</hi> good wherein thou art a Lord,</l>
                        <l>And haſt remained certain, by-paſt yeers,</l>
                        <l>In Parliament; in number of the Peers.</l>
                        <l>The laſt is this, which makes a threefold tie,</l>
                        <l>I ſtand ingaged, by affinitie;</l>
                        <l>Theſe three may challenge, ſince they all are true,</l>
                        <l>A dutifull remembrance of thy due.</l>
                        <l>And were it not I partiall ſhould be held,</l>
                        <l>I would expreſſe thee ſearcely Paralleld.</l>
                        <l>But I forbear, becauſe thy fame doth flie,</l>
                        <l>Beyond the reach of my arreſted eye:</l>
                        <l>Continue ſtill in favour, wealth, and fame,</l>
                        <l>And honours, encreaſe on thy Noble name.</l>
                        <l>And if curſt envie, doth affirm I flatter,</l>
                        <l>Yet can my lines, not make thee worſe, nor better.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:36"/>
                     <head>TO The Honourable <hi>William Lenthall</hi> Eſq. Speaker of the Honourable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I hat' all'vill men.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I have all evill men, <hi>the chair have I,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To ſit and plead ſpeak and impartially.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>THou waſt found fitteſt after long debate,</l>
                        <l>To be chief Speaker in the Chair of State,</l>
                        <l>A place ſo high, ſo weighty, honourable,</l>
                        <l>Thou hadſt not had it, hadſt thou not been able.</l>
                        <l>Nor when thou hadſt it, had thou not been juſt,</l>
                        <l>Thou hadſt not had it; ſo long in thy truſt.</l>
                        <l>But thou haſt prov'd ſo painfull, pregnant, wiſe,</l>
                        <l>Appear'd ſo upright in brave <hi>Englands</hi> eyes,</l>
                        <l>That ſo long as the greateſt Councell ſit,</l>
                        <l>By all conſents thou maiſt inherit it.</l>
                        <l>The mouth of thoſe who ſits about that throne,</l>
                        <l>Speaks all their mindes, and yet thou art but one.</l>
                        <l>To thee each grievance muſt be given out,</l>
                        <l>Then prudently thou ſpeaks it round about.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:36"/>And then thoſe worthies what they finde is beſt,</l>
                        <l>Return't to thee, by thee to be expreſt.</l>
                        <l>VVhich thou by Order, cauſeſt to diſpence,</l>
                        <l>In method, manner, to divulge the ſence</l>
                        <l>Of their deſigne, ſo that thou ſtill remains,</l>
                        <l>Full of conceptions, and unceſſant pains.</l>
                        <l>The place belongs moſt properly to thee,</l>
                        <l>I wiſh thou wouldſt ſpeak once a word for mee.</l>
                        <l>They fay that Poëts ſtill continue poor,</l>
                        <l>And this makes me ſo often at the door.</l>
                        <l>But if thou pleaſeſt, when the Houſe is ſet,</l>
                        <l>Think on my ſervice, and declare my debt:</l>
                        <l>I know I may juſt curteſie receive,</l>
                        <l>Amongſt ſuch Maſters, having much to crave:</l>
                        <l>I hope you will not let me praiſe your pay,</l>
                        <l>And yet my ſelf come craving every day.</l>
                        <l>You all are gods, your actions ever pure,</l>
                        <l>And I preſume, becauſe your Creature.</l>
                        <l>Yet I appeal unto that place ſo high,</l>
                        <l>VVhich is eſtabliſht in fidelity.</l>
                        <l>VVhere thou doſt ſit, whoſe vertues I adore,</l>
                        <l>I kiſſe thy hand, and ſo I ſay no more.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:37"/>
                     <head>TO <hi>THE HONOURABLE</hi> JAMES FIENNES.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>1. My fanſi'ſeen.</l>
                        <l>2. I ſee ſinnes aim.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>My fanſie ſeen, I ſee ſineneſſe aime;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Theſe are the juſt Characters of thy Name.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>I Shall be thought to have ſome ſlight intent,</l>
                        <l>Or that I ſpeak by way of complement;</l>
                        <l>Nor can I ſhun, but they will cenſure me,</l>
                        <l>Upon the ſight of what I ſay to thee.</l>
                        <l>But I appeal, unto the mindes of thoſe,</l>
                        <l>If thou haſt any, who art term'd thy foes;</l>
                        <l>They will bear witneſſe, that I have a Theam,</l>
                        <l>In venturing to write upon thy Name:</l>
                        <l>Which neither Poët, Prophet, nor Divine,</l>
                        <l>Can change the Nature, it is truly fien,</l>
                        <l>And what is Fien? But onely the extract,</l>
                        <l>Of all things good, which wholly is compact,</l>
                        <l>In one entire, and formall ſhape of thing,</l>
                        <l>Which, if they ask me where it is? Muſt bring</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelf in preſence, proving it is thine</l>
                        <l>Or thou art it; that brave and Noble <hi>Fien:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which yet I finde, is but a branch that ſprings,</l>
                        <l>From ſuch re-fiens; as are renowned things.</l>
                        <l>Thus of ſuch ancient Worthies art thou ſprung,</l>
                        <l>But wilt exceed them all, thou art but young.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:37"/>
                     <head>To the Right Worſhipfull Sir JOHN MERRICK, Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>1. I kno' merci's hire.</l>
                        <l>2. I, one, me'ker, rich.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To vertue, knowledge, honour, I aſpire,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>But moſt to mercy,</hi> I know Mercies hire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>VVHat? Richer, and yet meeker? This is much,</l>
                        <l>One may be meeker, but both, ſeldome ſuch,</l>
                        <l>This argueth goodneſſe; addeth to thy worth,</l>
                        <l>To have ſuch Emblems made to ſet thee forth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Riches is much, but meekneſſe is far more,</l>
                        <l>That one is earthly, tother's heavenly ſtore,</l>
                        <l>But now a third thing, in thy name doth ſit;</l>
                        <l>It ſays, <hi>I, one,</hi> but what a one is it?</l>
                        <l>Add then theſe two, unite this I, and one,</l>
                        <l>And you ſhall ſee, it is nothing but <hi>John.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Joyn then the ſumme, and you ſhall ſee a Theam,</l>
                        <l>Too high for me to write on ſuch a Name.</l>
                        <l>But one thing yet, leſt partiall I appear;</l>
                        <l>If any ask me why thy Name is here?</l>
                        <l>I muſt return this anſwer, let them know,</l>
                        <l>I have two reaſons, which I truly owe</l>
                        <l>Unto thy vertues, and which ties me to it,</l>
                        <l>And theſe are ſure, the cauſes why I do it;</l>
                        <l>The one is this, thou hadſt a ſpeciall hand,</l>
                        <l>In all this Warfare, and a high command,</l>
                        <l>And wer't beloved by his Excellence,</l>
                        <l>A cauſe to me, of no ſmall conſequence.</l>
                        <l>Theſe two together, with the love I bear,</l>
                        <l>To thee; makes me, ſtay and conſider here:</l>
                        <l>That ſince I have not better things to grant,</l>
                        <l>Accept of theſe Sir, and you ſhall not want.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:38"/>
                     <head>TO THE Right VVorſhipfull Sir <hi>Henrie Mervyn,</hi> Knight; my Father in Law.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Here in my vrne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Here in my urne,</hi> when death hath paid its debt,</l>
                        <l>Above this box, or Cabin ſhall be ſet,</l>
                        <l>Th' abſtract of knowledge, Learnings highest parts,</l>
                        <l>Chief piece of Nature, notable in Arts.</l>
                        <l>All theſe combin'd, which way you pleaſe to turn,</l>
                        <l>Lies here intomb'd, or reſts, <hi>Here in my Urn.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>AMongſt thoſe worthies, I were much to blame,</l>
                        <l>If I ſhould not remember thee, with them,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe pregnant parts, appeared ſo abroad,</l>
                        <l>Thy skill tranſcended like a demy God:</l>
                        <l>Thou couldſt, within thy cloſet, compaſſe all,</l>
                        <l>And bring to light the ſecrets of the Ball,</l>
                        <l>And truly ſtill, contrive within a ſpan,</l>
                        <l>VVhat may be travaild in the age of man.</l>
                        <l>Couldſt dip within the Oceans deep, and yet,</l>
                        <l>Keep diſtance, at the ſelf-ſame time with it,</l>
                        <l>Prevent the perils therein; which lay hid,</l>
                        <l>Give notice likewiſe to the blind, who did,</l>
                        <l>Not dare to dive, but did forbear to be,</l>
                        <l>So bold to venture if they wanted thêe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:38"/>Thy skill could reach unto the Starry sky,</l>
                        <l>And know the ſecrets therein, by and by,</l>
                        <l>Thoſe private periods on the Compaſſe ſtands,</l>
                        <l>Did all lye open inſtant in thy hands.</l>
                        <l>Nothing lay ſecret, but by thee was ſeen,</l>
                        <l>That is, or ſhall be, or hath ever been,</l>
                        <l>Thou waſt a feather of the Soveraign Wing,</l>
                        <l>To flie, and ſerve thy ſometime Maſter, King.</l>
                        <l>Thou alſo hadſt the ſole command by Sea,</l>
                        <l>And every one did homage unto thee:</l>
                        <l>Scarce one, but one, ſo favour'd in the Court,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet hadſt been, had not the time cut ſhort,</l>
                        <l>Of famous <hi>James,</hi> thy Royall Maſter, than,</l>
                        <l>Whou could diſtinguiſh wele twixt man and man:</l>
                        <l>Thou art of thoſe, and it is known moſt true,</l>
                        <l>Accompted Noble, by thy birth as due;</l>
                        <l>Nor are thy high deſervings leſſened yet,</l>
                        <l>(But thou forbeareth to be ſeen in it.)</l>
                        <l>Stands as the Center where men do reſort,</l>
                        <l>To learn thy knowledge, wherein they come ſhort.</l>
                        <l>Thou lov's to look, and with indifferent eye,</l>
                        <l>Behold the changes of the time paſſe by,</l>
                        <l>Elſe hadſt thou doubtleſſe had the ſole command.</l>
                        <l>On either ſide, within this troubled Land.</l>
                        <l>For few or none, if I ſhould finde it fit,</l>
                        <l>For to declare, exceeds thy worth, thy wit.</l>
                        <l>For which reſpects, I may include thy Name,</l>
                        <l>As adding ſo much to the worth of them,</l>
                        <l>Whom I do chuſe moſt chiefly, for my charge,</l>
                        <l>To play upon their Noble Names at large;</l>
                        <l>And if my duty challeng'd not a tye,</l>
                        <l>Upon my thoughts, I would ſay more, but I,</l>
                        <l>Will ceaſe; becauſe thy worth is ſo well known,</l>
                        <l>Write what I will, I give thee but thine own.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:39"/>
                     <head>TO THE <hi>RJGHT WORSHJPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL</hi> Sir WILLIAM BELFOURE Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>1. Lofam' I will be ever.</l>
                        <l>2. I will be ru'l of fame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Lo fame I will be ever, I will be rule of fame.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>This is no fiction, but thy very Name.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>WHen <hi>England</hi> did impartially imploy,</l>
                        <l>The Nations ſpirits, for them for to fight.</l>
                        <l>They did deſire the honour to enjoy,</l>
                        <l>Thee, in the fields, for their foes deſpight;</l>
                        <l>And with conſent, thee to a place did call,</l>
                        <l>Which was indeed, their ſecond Generall.</l>
                        <l>Lo how their high intentions unto thee,</l>
                        <l>And thy performance did ſo well agree.</l>
                        <l>Thou prov'd ſo faithfull in their Royall Tow'r,</l>
                        <l>They almoſt did idolatrize <hi>Belfoure.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But they peceiv'd thy ſpirit was too high,</l>
                        <l>To be ſo private, in extremitie.</l>
                        <l>And thus reſolv'd, to ſatisfie the eyes,</l>
                        <l>Of thoſe who long'd to ſee ſome enterprize</l>
                        <l>Perform'd by thee; but with a ſad goodnight,</l>
                        <l>When thou departed, from thy former right,</l>
                        <l>There, were they ſorry, that thou ſhouldſt go hence,</l>
                        <l>Yet muſt ſubmit to ſuch a fair pretence,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:39"/>And then their care, into a terrour turn'd,</l>
                        <l>The multitude made much ado and mourn'd,</l>
                        <l>Suſpected, and expreſt themſelves diſmaid,</l>
                        <l>In jealous doubts, the Tow'r might be betraid.</l>
                        <l>Yet they muſt part, thy preſence muſt be gone,</l>
                        <l>Thou muſt be mounted, thou wert called on;</l>
                        <l>Thy by-paſt vertues to thy valour-yeilds,</l>
                        <l>A Saint in private, Lyon in the Fields,</l>
                        <l>It was enough, to hear thy Noble name,</l>
                        <l>Thy conſtant courage, did thy worth proclaim;</l>
                        <l>And with ſuch action, as thou didſt perform,</l>
                        <l>Prov'd dexterous in many dangerous ſtorm,</l>
                        <l>I did behold thee, when thou hadſt to do,</l>
                        <l>In publike fights, and private counſels too.</l>
                        <l>I ſaw thy practice and thy prudence fit,</l>
                        <l>Renownd for courage, and cride up for wit,</l>
                        <l>The fierce encounters which did cruſh thy foes,</l>
                        <l>Triumphing on them by undaunted blowes,</l>
                        <l>Did move an Eccho, made the Mountains ſhake,</l>
                        <l>And forc'd thy foes to call abake, abake,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Belfours</hi> abroad, O do not venture then,</l>
                        <l>To re-encounter, leſt ye loſe your men:</l>
                        <l>This was thy practice in the place of Warre,</l>
                        <l>Thus did thou then, but now behold you are,</l>
                        <l>Injoyd in peace, thy preſence is at hand,</l>
                        <l>At home, and hence, thus haſt thou had command:</l>
                        <l>And in each place, where ever thou hadſt truſt,</l>
                        <l>None will accuſe thee, thou prov'd wondrous juſt,</l>
                        <l>Thou prov'd a pattern in each place of Note,</l>
                        <l>An honour to the Nation of the Scote;</l>
                        <l>From whence thou cam'ſt, and didſt thy being take,</l>
                        <l>But I will ceaſe, it is in vain to make</l>
                        <l>More Lines, unleſſe I had more Letters too,</l>
                        <l>That I may know more promptly what to do.</l>
                        <l>And ſo reſolve to ſay no more, but reſt,</l>
                        <l>My thoughts are ſuch, they cannot be expreſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:40"/>
                     <head>TO THE <hi>RJGHT WORSHJPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL</hi> Sir PHILIP STEPLETON, Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>1. O thy pleaſant lips.</l>
                        <l>2. Help on, pitie ſtill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>O thy pleaſant lips, <hi>farre from ſpeaking ill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Make good thy Anagram;</hi> Help on, pitie ſtill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epig.</head>
                        <l>I ſhould be much aſham'd, to ſee thee look,</l>
                        <l>And not perceive thy Name within my Book,</l>
                        <l>Who having had ſuch favours at thy hand,</l>
                        <l>May well afford, a room for thee to ſtand;</l>
                        <l>Amongſt thoſe Worthies where you daily ſit,</l>
                        <l>Thy many vertues well deſerveth it.</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Romans</hi> who were ruled by a ſeat,</l>
                        <l>Of worthy Senat's, had none more compleat,</l>
                        <l>Then thou who haſt a double burthen taken,</l>
                        <l>With heart and hand, haſt not the Cauſe forſaken,</l>
                        <l>Thy valour, and diſcretion did agree,</l>
                        <l>In open fight, I oft perceived thee,</l>
                        <l>A ſometime ſecond, to that Noble Lord,</l>
                        <l>To whoſe decrees thou truly didſt accord,</l>
                        <l>Abroad a pattern often didſt appear,</l>
                        <l>And for thy wiſedome art renowned here,</l>
                        <l>Thus haſt thou had a hand in every thing,</l>
                        <l>To reunite the State, unto the King.</l>
                        <l>Thy double vertues, doth deſerve renoune,</l>
                        <l>And Lawrell Boughes, to loyall <hi>Stepletone.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:40"/>
                     <head>TO THE <hi>RJGHT WORSHJPF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL</hi> Sir JOHN CLATWORTHYE, Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anag.</head>
                        <l>Now thy holj care.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Now thy holy care, <hi>and ayd's requir'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy knowledge and thy vertues are admir'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>VVHat? But a few prove loyall to the State?</l>
                        <l>When all the Iriſh Rebels, made debate,</l>
                        <l>And of thoſe few it is my onely aim,</l>
                        <l>To ſpeak of thee, becauſe I know not them.</l>
                        <l>I finde thy vertues makes thee much renown'd,</l>
                        <l>Thy wayes are upright, and thy wits profound<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou art a Member of that Houſe ſo high,</l>
                        <l>Which is a Touchſtone to fidelitie.</l>
                        <l>Of ancient ſtock, which addeth to thy fame:</l>
                        <l>A Noble Nature, and a Worthy Name:</l>
                        <l>Who ſometimes hath ſhew'd friendſhip unto me,</l>
                        <l>Shall then my Book, not bear the Name of thee?</l>
                        <l>Yes whilſt it laſts, thy Name ſhall live therein,</l>
                        <l>And when its loſt, thy praiſes ſhall begin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:41"/>
                     <head>TO The VVorſhipfull his moſt Reſpected, WILLIAM JEPSONE.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I am one eſpj evill.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I am one (<hi>in all things</hi>) eſpy evill.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I ſeek the good, but ſhun, deſpiſe the Devill.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>AN ACCROSTICK SONNET.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>W</hi>iſe <hi>Maro</hi> pend, <hi>Mecoenas</hi> worthy praiſe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I</hi>nſtately ſtile, in high, and lofty phraſe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>L</hi>ikewiſe my lines can give no leſſe to thee,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>L</hi>eſſe of themſelves, though they of nature be;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I</hi>n civill things, ſo prudent and ſo juſt,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A</hi>nd, <hi>one eſpying evill,</hi> ſhunning luſt.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>M</hi>irrour of vertue, active in the truth,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>J</hi>ngenuous, gentle, ſcorning idle ſloth;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>E</hi>vill eſpying, and one purſuing good;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>P</hi>rudently pious, one of Noble blood:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>S</hi>incere, ſo wiſe, and vertuous in thy minde,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O</hi>ne who to me, hath proved truly kinde:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>N</hi>othing ſhall therefore make me to forbear,</l>
                        <l>but want of Letters to extoll thee here.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:41"/>
                     <head>TO The VVorſhipfull Sir <hi>Charles Erskin,</hi> Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>1. Search, kill Siners.</l>
                        <l>Shin's liker Caeſar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>VVHat praiſe may my <hi>impartiall</hi> pen expreſſe,</l>
                        <l>And yet thy <hi>worth</hi> not to the full <hi>confeſſe?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor need I urge, to make my matter <hi>fine,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Falſe flouriſhings, nor can I reach the line</l>
                        <l>Of thy <hi>profound</hi> approved prudence, neither;</l>
                        <l>Who <hi>ſearches</hi> firſt, then <hi>kils</hi> the <hi>ſinners;</hi> rather</l>
                        <l>Then thou wilt not, <hi>ſhine liker Caeſar,</hi> and</l>
                        <l>Though thou be young, gain honour to that Land,</l>
                        <l>From whence thou cam'ſt, and for thy worth who chus'd thee,</l>
                        <l>To ſend thee here; and for thy faith have us'd thee:</l>
                        <l>In ſtate affairs, <hi>ſearch</hi> and <hi>kill ſinners;</hi> then</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Shine liker Caeſar,</hi> more then other men.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:42"/>
                     <head>To the Worſhipful ALEXANDER POPHAM, Eſquire.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Read here an 'xample.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Of all unconquer'd worth,</hi> Read, here, an 'xample,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy Name, and fame, ſufficiently is ample.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>TO thee, I come, brave Conquerour of <hi>fame,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of valour, vertue, and <hi>Heroick</hi> Name,</l>
                        <l>And on this <hi>Stage,</hi> or new impreſſed <hi>ſtamp,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Or in this <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> where <hi>Englands</hi> Worthies Camp,</l>
                        <l>About brave <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and where each do ſhine,</l>
                        <l>I repreſent that Noble worth of thine:</l>
                        <l>By <hi>Birth</hi> in number with the <hi>best,</hi> and yet,</l>
                        <l>Thou reſts not there, but addeth unto it,</l>
                        <l>By acts of <hi>honour</hi> in the higheſt kinde,</l>
                        <l>The parallels of <hi>Alexanders</hi> minde:</l>
                        <l>What paſſive patience hath importun'd thee?</l>
                        <l>Thy Edifices ruines witneſſe be:</l>
                        <l>What <hi>vaſt eſtate,</hi> by tyranny deſtroid?</l>
                        <l>Which thy innumered <hi>Anceſtors</hi> injoyd?</l>
                        <l>Yea what expences, haſt thou pleaſt to ſpend?</l>
                        <l>Thy faith and freedome, truly to defend.</l>
                        <l>Nor didſt thou, yet, here limit thy delight,</l>
                        <l>But all thy curious <hi>buildings</hi> didſt thou quit,</l>
                        <l>With great eſtate; (the <hi>Grandor</hi> of that glory)</l>
                        <l>Seem'd, but to thee, like <hi>Eſop</hi> in his ſtory.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Mounted,</hi> marcht in moſt <hi>Magnifick</hi> manner,</l>
                        <l>VVhen <hi>Mars</hi> threw out, his ſacrifizing Banner;</l>
                        <l>Bedect with <hi>Emblems</hi> of pale <hi>death,</hi> and darts,</l>
                        <l>To dull the ſences of ſubmiſſive hearts.</l>
                        <l>Yet all was nothing, when they were combinde,</l>
                        <l>Nor could they conquer <hi>Alexanders</hi> minde.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:42"/>
                     <head>For the Worſhipful, <hi>DENZAL HOLLIS Eſquire.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Holds in Zeal.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>REader,</hi> be <hi>rev'rend</hi> all the time thou ſtands</l>
                        <l>And hath our famous <hi>Holles</hi> in thy hands,</l>
                        <l>Who, though the ſin <hi>Apoſtacie</hi> prevail</l>
                        <l>Yet changes not, but he ſtill <hi>Holds in Zeal.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Religions encreaſe, he hath ever <hi>aim'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I mean the true <hi>Religion,</hi> which is nam'd</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and purely doth apply,</l>
                        <l>Himſelf thereto, with an <hi>impartial</hi> Eye;</l>
                        <l>Shun's faithleſſe <hi>Factions, Errours,</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Still <hi>Holds in Zeal,</hi> and pow'rfully convinces</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Connivings,</hi> ſides not, with <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> bands,</l>
                        <l>But for the Tim's <hi>oppoſed</hi> Truth, he ſtands.</l>
                        <l>Wiſe, holy <hi>Holles,</hi> Heavens let thee not fail,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pattron</hi> of <hi>Piety,</hi> thou who <hi>Holds in Zeal,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Long may'ſt thou live, renowned for thy worth,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe <hi>Actions</hi> well become thy honoured birth.</l>
                        <l>And thou who run the <hi>hazard</hi> of thy bloud</l>
                        <l>For thy Religion, and thy Countrey's good;</l>
                        <l>Nor ſtood upon, the loſſe of thy Eſtate,</l>
                        <l>Nor greater <hi>dangers,</hi> nor the <hi>higheſt</hi> hate</l>
                        <l>Thou could'ſt <hi>incurre,</hi> but conſtantly did'ſt ſtand,</l>
                        <l>To all theſe things, ſign'd with thy heart and hand.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W: M,</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:43"/>
                     <head>For the Worſhipfull, <hi>JOHN GOODWIN,</hi> Eſquire,</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Anagr. Ho! I winn Good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HO! <hi>I winn Good,</hi> Doſt win it where thou ſits?</l>
                        <l>No, That's enough to win men from their wits:</l>
                        <l>The whole Petitions of this plundered Land</l>
                        <l>Muſt be preſented to thy piou hand:</l>
                        <l>The bloudy, thirſty, ſtarving Souldier, greeves,</l>
                        <l>Haunts your Committee, every day beleeves</l>
                        <l>To have relief: and by Petitions,</l>
                        <l>Calls in your eares, have pitty Sir upon's,</l>
                        <l>The handſom, and hard-favor'd widows, wooe,</l>
                        <l>They much importune, puts you to it too,</l>
                        <l>Officers wives, and Waggoners conveen,</l>
                        <l>At your Committee, and are alwayes ſeen,</l>
                        <l>Soliciting, yea threatning you for food,</l>
                        <l>Is this the way then, that ye <hi>Win your Good?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>No, 'tis by granting favour unto them,</l>
                        <l>VVho ſtand in need, that way ye <hi>win your Name.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And were it not, your goodneſſe did appeare</l>
                        <l>In all your pains, you had not had the Chaire.</l>
                        <l>Brave Noble Sir, then ſince ye are ſo free,</l>
                        <l>Looſe not the <hi>Good ye VVin,</hi> prove good to me.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:43"/>
                     <head>For the VVorſhipful MICHAEL NOBLE ESQVIRE.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Lo men be Clay,</l>
                        <l>Call him Noble.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In Heaven Archangel, in Earth,</hi> we call him Noble.</l>
                        <l>Lo Men be Clay, <hi>a Two fold praiſe, one trouble.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THy real goodneſſe, and thy noble Name,</l>
                        <l>Requires me to remember thee with them,</l>
                        <l>VVhoſe high deſervings, and renowned praiſe</l>
                        <l>(In ſuch Encomiums as thou ſeeſt I raiſe)</l>
                        <l>Are here inrol'd, as Emblems to remain</l>
                        <l>And ſignes of Honour, Trophies in a Train,</l>
                        <l>To Eternize your Vertues, Names, and Fames,</l>
                        <l>So long as <hi>London</hi> ſtands upon the Thames.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:44"/>
                     <head>To the truly Honourable Collonel, Collonel <hi>Audelay Mervin,</hi> my brother in Law.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Adieu al my ru'ne.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Adieu al my ru'ne, <hi>reſolutely I dare,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Withſtand, contemn, all frowning Fortunes far<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonot.</head>
                        <l>WHat ſhall I ſay, for to extoll thy <hi>Praiſe?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which formerly is not expres't of theſe</l>
                        <l>To whom I writ? So that without offence</l>
                        <l>I think I may, extract the <hi>Quinteſſence</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of moſt thoſe <hi>Vertues,</hi> which are here <hi>allow'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And yet may my <hi>Hiperboles</hi> make good;</l>
                        <l>It cannot leſſen their <hi>Eſteem,</hi> for they</l>
                        <l>Are truly <hi>valued,</hi> therefore muſt I ſay,</l>
                        <l>Though thou art <hi>young,</hi> yet are thy parts ſo rare,</l>
                        <l>Ther's no diſparage, freely to compare</l>
                        <l>Thy Pregnancie, and thy approved Fame</l>
                        <l>May well be coupled, and annex'd to them:</l>
                        <l>Thy high Diſcent, heroick actions too</l>
                        <l>Makes me take freedom, for the thing I doe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:44"/>
                     <head>To the Right Worſhipful, Sir <hi>Richard Strode, Knight.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Rid Chriſts order.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Stop thoſe who ſtrive to ſtray from Iuſtice border,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hereby thou ſhalt gal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Fame, and</hi> Rid Chriſts order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>STay yet my <hi>Muſe,</hi> for as the caſe doth ſtand,</l>
                        <l>Thou art too <hi>raſh,</hi> and tak'ſt too much in hand,</l>
                        <l>Doſt thou intend of active <hi>Strode</hi> to write?</l>
                        <l>Though thou indeed wilt prove moſt imperfit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>To pen his praiſe, when <hi>Plato</hi> might come ſhort,</l>
                        <l>If he were <hi>living,</hi> and would labour for't.</l>
                        <l>His noble birth is equall with the beſt.</l>
                        <l>His other <hi>
                              <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertues</hi> cannot be expreſt;</l>
                        <l>Hath he not <hi>loſt,</hi> and left his <hi>ſtate</hi> behind;</l>
                        <l>And hath <hi>endeavor'd,</hi> with a faithful mind,</l>
                        <l>To make this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſtand engag'd, and <hi>grant</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>My skill is <hi>ſcarce;</hi> though <hi>I</hi> no matter want</l>
                        <l>To write <hi>upon,</hi> in penning of his <hi>praiſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And me approve, to crown his head with <hi>Bayes.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who was ſo <hi>forward,</hi> for to ſerve the <hi>State</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He did not ſtand, as others to <hi>debate,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What place was beſt, according to his <hi>Birth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Or fit for <hi>gain,</hi> or equall to his <hi>worth,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But put himſelf, for <hi>Devons</hi> good to be,</l>
                        <l>Upon imployment, night, nor day was free<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor did he ceaſe, thus with his Sword to ſtand</l>
                        <l>But with his Pen, hath pleaded for this Land;</l>
                        <l>Nor reſts he <hi>there,</hi> but ſets himſelf at <hi>odds,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Againſt all <hi>Perſons,</hi> wbo by practice <hi>plods</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>As he <hi>perceives;</hi> by ſelf-conceited <hi>skill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To do the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> Priviledges ill,</l>
                        <l>Then in a word, let <hi>Strode</hi> be ſtill renown'd,</l>
                        <l>In whom thoſe vertues ſo much do <hi>abound.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:45"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>Thomas Adams,</hi> Lord Major.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Or I add more alm's as Th'am,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Our Londoners Thames, adds much Alms to them:</l>
                        <l>Yet I do more, Or I add more al'ms as Th'am.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>MOſt admir'd, vertuous, Governour <hi>ſupream,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whoſe well-deſerving actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gaind the Name,</l>
                        <l>As only fit, to ſway the <hi>Sword,</hi> and bear</l>
                        <l>The Badge of <hi>Honour,</hi> ſo renowned here.</l>
                        <l>In time of War, a token of ſuch state</l>
                        <l>It were too <hi>high</hi> for me, for to relate.</l>
                        <l>Amongſt ſuch <hi>Members,</hi> of admired worth,</l>
                        <l>By all conſents, to chuſe thee only forth.</l>
                        <l>And for the truſt, they truly put in thee,</l>
                        <l>They all accompted it <hi>abſurdity</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To ſtrive, or ſtudy as they uſe, or wooe it,</l>
                        <l>But cal'd thee there, a<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> thou hadſt bin to it,</l>
                        <l>And ſolemnized, thy new elected Name,</l>
                        <l>With no leſſe new Inventions on the <hi>Theam.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>VVhat high <hi>Attendance</hi> to thy Trains allow'd?</l>
                        <l>Enough to move a <hi>Monarch</hi> to be proud?</l>
                        <l>Yet ſuch is that <hi>unmatched</hi> mind of thine,</l>
                        <l>Thou <hi>Values</hi> not theſe <hi>outwards,</hi> but doſt ſhine</l>
                        <l>By thoſe reflects, which from thy <hi>Vertues</hi> flyes,</l>
                        <l>And ſo yeelds comfort to <hi>Spectators</hi> eyes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>That courſe which <hi>Cuſtome</hi> for a Right doth claime,</l>
                        <l>Shall ceaſe, and no more change its Majors Name.</l>
                        <l>Becauſe it onely changed with intent,</l>
                        <l>To chuſe a new one for amendement.</l>
                        <l>Long mayſt thou live, <hi>Lord Major</hi> and remain</l>
                        <l>Renownd in <hi>London,</hi> till the Floods refraine</l>
                        <l>To flow, or fall and till the Thames return,</l>
                        <l>And change its Nature in a Fire to burn.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:45"/>
                     <head>The Right Honourable, Lord Major, and Court of Aldermen.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HEre <hi>Adam</hi> on his <hi>Paradizial</hi> Throne</l>
                        <l>Is <hi>Circled</hi> with his <hi>Off-Spring</hi> thereupon;</l>
                        <l>Or view <hi>Him</hi> ſitting on a <hi>Seat</hi> ſo high,</l>
                        <l>And repreſenting of a <hi>Majeſtie,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>VVith Four and twenty <hi>Elders</hi> in a <hi>Train</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Attending on him, while he doth remain</l>
                        <l>Upon the <hi>Plane;</hi> yea one more yet you ſee,</l>
                        <l>But at his right hand, the <hi>Recorder</hi> be.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>everyone;</hi> becauſe I can not bring</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Themſelves;</hi> theſe letters, ſignifie the thing.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <p>
                        <figure/>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Behold out firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> Lord Major <hi>Chiefe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Surrounded with his <hi>Off-Spring,</hi> here in briefe:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Recorder, Knights,</hi> Grave Aldermen, and yet</l>
                        <l>I Place them all in order<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as they ſit.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>1 Renown'd <hi>Recorder,</hi> pregnant <hi>Glinn,</hi> in Law,</l>
                        <l>2 Knight <hi>Rainton</hi> likewiſe, for his worth I ſaw,</l>
                        <l>3 Brave <hi>Pennington,</hi> ſo prudent, wiſe, and juſt,</l>
                        <l>4 Knight <hi>Williſton,</hi> ſo upright in his truſt;</l>
                        <l>5 Applauded <hi>Atkins,</hi> famous for his Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>6 Knight <hi>Cordwell</hi> alſo, honoured to the death.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:46"/>7 Solatious <hi>Soums,</hi> Knight, be thou alſo <hi>crown'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>8 Grave, pious, <hi>Geer,</hi> Knight, likewiſe and renown'd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>9 Good <hi>Gerret,</hi> Knight, in Vertues with the beſt,</l>
                        <l>10 And worthy <hi>Warner</hi> ought to be exprest;</l>
                        <l>11 Renowned, Reverend, <hi>Reinoldſon,</hi> ſo wiſe,</l>
                        <l>12 And gracious <hi>Gerrer,</hi> ſo in each mans eyes.</l>
                        <l>13 Commended <hi>Clerk</hi> thy knowledge doth excell,</l>
                        <l>14 Beloved <hi>Langham,</hi> thy worth I cannot tell;</l>
                        <l>15 Admired <hi>Andrew's</hi> modeſt, free of Pride,</l>
                        <l>16 Let faithfull <hi>Ponks,</hi> in memory abide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>17 But <hi>Bunce</hi> thy bounty cannot be forgot,</l>
                        <l>18 And <hi>Gibs,</hi> much goodneſſe falleth to thy lot;</l>
                        <l>19 See cheerfull <hi>Chambers,</hi> Cabinet of worth,</l>
                        <l>20 Firm <hi>Foot</hi> in friendſhip, London paints thee forth:</l>
                        <l>21 Kind <hi>Kindrick</hi> courteous, conſtant, active, and</l>
                        <l>22 Couragious <hi>Cullom,</hi> fit for high Command;</l>
                        <l>23 Eſteem brave <hi>Edmonds,</hi> eternize his Name,</l>
                        <l>24 Acknowledge <hi>Evere,</hi> admir'd for his Fame;</l>
                        <l>25 Behold brave <hi>Byde,</hi> bedeck'd with vertues high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>26 Thrice worthy <hi>Witham,</hi> keeps a ſimpathie,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And makes a Court of Aldermen, and Knights,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe glory ſhines, even like as many Lights,</l>
                        <l>And all in one do contribute their skill</l>
                        <l>To keep this famous City free from ill.</l>
                        <l>Thus have I plai'd impartially on their Names,</l>
                        <l>Being ly'd to <hi>Termes,</hi> and <hi>Titles,</hi> two extreams,</l>
                        <l>But briefly thus, I boldly do afford,</l>
                        <l>And put their Names for ever on Record.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:46"/>
                     <head>To the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>John Northcute</hi> Knight.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr,</head>
                        <l>He cheriſht honnour,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>He cheriſht honnour, <hi>when he was at warre,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And ſtill goes on in this ſame ſtraine as farre.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THy wiſdom, valour, and fidelity,</l>
                        <l>Thy knowledge actions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and thy conſtancy,</l>
                        <l>Firſt mov<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d the Kingdom cal for thee, as fit,</l>
                        <l>In its High Court, and Councell for to ſit,</l>
                        <l>From thence a two fold teſtimony too</l>
                        <l>Thou didſt afford<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> couragiouſly didſt do,</l>
                        <l>In open fields, and there didſt fight, and ſtand,</l>
                        <l>VVith constant mind, and an heroick hand:</l>
                        <l>Thy loyall ſelf, ſequeſtrate for a time,</l>
                        <l>For no offence, nor for a ſinfull crime,</l>
                        <l>Yet there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with patience, then thou didſt ſubmit,</l>
                        <l>Nor didſt thou therefore ſhrink aſide at it:</l>
                        <l>But didſt continue to the State, ſo true,</l>
                        <l>That I come ſhort to ſolemnize thy due.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:47"/>
                     <head>To the Right worſhipfull, Sir <hi>Samuel Roule.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Riſe me real ſoul.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Riſe my real ſoul, <hi>henceforth take no reſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Till thou enioy the ioy, is not expreſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>THy name, thy nature, and thy practice too,</l>
                        <l>Are all prepar'd, what they reſolve to do.</l>
                        <l>Thy name ſayes <hi>Riſe my real ſoul,</hi> no reſt,</l>
                        <l>Till thou injoy, the joy is not expreſt.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Thy nature likewiſe <hi>really</hi> is bent,</l>
                        <l>And to as early <hi>riſing</hi> gives conſent:</l>
                        <l>And then thy <hi>reall</hi> practice every day</l>
                        <l>Of early <hi>riſing,</hi> makes it good, I ſay.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The age of time, nor yet the times of year,</l>
                        <l>Nor loſſe of gain, nor wearied travels here,</l>
                        <l>Makes thee omit: but thou prevents the day</l>
                        <l>By early riſing, and makes haſt to pray.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:47"/>
                        <l>In publike place, and ſacred ſermons haunts,</l>
                        <l>Where ſchiſmes are not, amongſt proteſtants,</l>
                        <l>In number art one of that noble band,</l>
                        <l>Who for the Nations priviledges ſtand.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And in its ſervice ſent thy noble Sonne,</l>
                        <l>And freeborn heir, what more then could be done?</l>
                        <l>Thus to the State thy good extends, and I</l>
                        <l>Am likewiſe bound unto thy courteſie.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Wherefore in reaſon I could do no leſſe,</l>
                        <l>Then repreſent thy vertues in my Glaſſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:48"/>
                     <head>To the worſhipfull <hi>Anthonie Nicholls,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Anagr. T'ſchine holi alon.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>THough thy name ſaies, <hi>T'ſchine holi alon,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And where thou'rt ſet, thou doſt not ſhine but one</l>
                        <l>Yet lo thy vertues, like the Eaſtern ſtar,</l>
                        <l>Shines with thoſe worthies where thou placed are.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Their ſplendour adds unto that light of thine,</l>
                        <l>And they get encreaſe by thy glorious ſhine,</l>
                        <l>Be holy alſo, though not ſo alone,,</l>
                        <l>And ſtrive thou to be ſingular for one.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And as thy name comes nigh to ſay ſo much,</l>
                        <l>Still enterpriſe to make thy actions ſuch:</l>
                        <l>Shine holy ſtill, be upright in thy place,</l>
                        <l>Deferre not juſtice in a needfull caſe.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>For holy, juſt, the humble, meek, and true,</l>
                        <l>And ſuch as are not, ſhall receive their due.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:48"/>
                     <head>To the much honoured, Major Generall <hi>Edward Maſsie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Made wars's aid.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thy valour, vertue, have thee famous made,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Deſervedly thou art</hi> made wars's aide.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>MAy not my Muſe one ſonnet ſing, to raiſe</l>
                        <l>The famous name of <hi>Maſsies</hi> worthy praiſe?</l>
                        <l>May not my glaſſe, a glimps give of his glory,</l>
                        <l>Although deficient of ſo fine a Story?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yes, they may both be buſied in the ſame,</l>
                        <l>And yet ſcarce add one tittle to his fame:</l>
                        <l>'Tis not the dulneſſe of my Moſes wit,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet a glaſſe, that can diſcover it.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Yet ſince he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>h been active on this ſtage,</l>
                        <l>Where moſt thoſe worthies honours did ingage,</l>
                        <l>My Muſes muſick, ſhall make melodie,</l>
                        <l>And ſing his praiſe, ſo ſhall my glaſſe let ſee,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Though not himſelf, yet ſomething of that kind,</l>
                        <l>Words cannot well expreſſe ſo high a mind.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:49"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the worſhipfull</hi> Godfraie Boſſezile, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>If zeal is Gods Robe.</l>
                        <l>Gods zeal is before.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>If zeal is Gods Robe, <hi>ô Covet that ſtore,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Be covered therewith,</hi> Gods zeal is before.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigram.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>IF Vertue, Valour, Honour,</hi> and the reſt</l>
                        <l>Thy attributes which cannot be expreſt,</l>
                        <l>Such as is Wiſdom, Gravitie, and Wit,</l>
                        <l>Diſcretion, knowledge, in abundance fit,</l>
                        <l>Beſids that ſacred Excellence of Faith</l>
                        <l>Which thou haſt vow'd and ſeal'd unto the death.</l>
                        <l>Joyn'd with that favour, and that free good will</l>
                        <l>Which thou affords to others in their ill,</l>
                        <l>Makes me acknowledge that it is my part</l>
                        <l>Amongſt thoſe worthies, fitly to inſert</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelfe; and yet the rather ſince thou 'rt one</l>
                        <l>Who in this warfare haſt ſo freely gone,</l>
                        <l>And much expoz'd thy perſon for the State,</l>
                        <l>To tyranny and irreligious hate;</l>
                        <l>Thoſe things I ſay, ſhall keep alive thy name,</l>
                        <l>When after ages ſhall thy praiſe proclaime:</l>
                        <l>And Titan ſhall not undertake to riſe,</l>
                        <l>Nor run his race throughout the ſpangled skies:</l>
                        <l>Before the Trumpet of thy Fame forbeare</l>
                        <l>To ſound abroad thy high deſervings here,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:49"/>
                     <head>To the VVorſhipfull, Mr. <hi>Hue Kennedie.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Hee, even kind.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Endowd With divers vertues of the mind,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Such as is</hi> conſcience, knowledge, hee even kind.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>SInce in the wiſdom of a twofold ſtate,</l>
                        <l>(When matters ſtand at ſuch a high debate)</l>
                        <l>In their election they did look on thee,</l>
                        <l>Moſt proper for employment <hi>Kennedie:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>It was the good opinion of thy friends,</l>
                        <l>Who would intruſt thee in ſuch publike ends,</l>
                        <l>By which thou art in number one of thoſe,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe prudence ſhal ſuppres the Nations foes.</l>
                        <l>Go on therefore, joyn in that juſt deſigne,</l>
                        <l>Give God the glory, and the honours thine.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:50"/>
                     <head>To his worthy friend, <hi>Mr. Iohn Cheeſly,</hi> Secretary to the Commiſsioners for <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Hence is holy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>What he records, it is ſo far from folly,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>He pennes With prudence, and</hi> he hence is holy.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr:</head>
                        <l>REnowned <hi>Cheeſly,</hi> unto thee I ſpeak,</l>
                        <l>And for thy worth, unfained praiſe I ſeek</l>
                        <l>What perfect practice is performd by thee,</l>
                        <l>It cannot fully be expreſt by me:</l>
                        <l>But they appoint thee prompteſt, I averre,</l>
                        <l>For fitteſt pen-man, wiſeſt Secretair.</l>
                        <l>Ioyn then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t iudgment which thou doſt ingage</l>
                        <l>The honour of thy Nation l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>es in pledge,</l>
                        <l>Add thy aſsiſtance, intimate thy will,</l>
                        <l>Require performance prorogate no ill,</l>
                        <l>And then no doubt thou wilt be, I beleeve,</l>
                        <l>Fit for employment, more ſuperlative.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:50"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To the Honourable, and Right worſhipfull, Sir</hi> Archibald Iohnſtoun, <hi>Lord</hi> Wareſtone.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Sober, and juſt, holi Shrin.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Thy name ſaies <hi>Sober, juſt and holi Shrine:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>So that by Nature thou muſt be divine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>TO be ſo honour'd and eſteem'd ſo hie,</l>
                        <l>And ſo promoted, in a Kingdoms Ey,</l>
                        <l>And yet be ſober in ſo great a truſt,</l>
                        <l>Declares thee truly Noble, ſurely juſt.</l>
                        <l>But then to be ſo holy and divine,</l>
                        <l>Of all theſe vertues for to be the ſhrine,</l>
                        <l>Is ſomewhat far above my rurall pen,</l>
                        <l>To paraphraſe upon ſuch pious men.</l>
                        <l>Thy prudent practice in affairs of State</l>
                        <l>Are things beyond my knowledge to relate.</l>
                        <l>Thy Art in learning is ſo eminent,</l>
                        <l>And reaches ſo above my Element,</l>
                        <l>That if I ſtrive to walk into that aire,</l>
                        <l>I ſtand in danger, leſt I periſh there.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:51"/>
                     <head>To the Right worſhipfull Sir Oliver Fleming.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Vſe firm religion.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Vſe firm religion,</hi> this imports thy name,</l>
                        <l>Let then thy practiſe alwaies be the ſame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>THy Name, thy Nature, and thy practiſe too</l>
                        <l>Iuvites thee to <hi>uſe firm religion, doe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Even as the number of theſe letters lead</l>
                        <l>What theſe Characters ſpell, let practiſe road:</l>
                        <l>But why ſhould I take on me to adviſe</l>
                        <l>Thy Noble ſelf, whoſe conſtant enterpriſe</l>
                        <l>Is to perſwade the people to go on</l>
                        <l>In zeal, and to <hi>Vſe firm Religion.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor yet is this the ſcope of thy deſigne,</l>
                        <l>Nor full intent, but Morralls with divine,</l>
                        <l>Thou contributes, ſo by a twofold Care,</l>
                        <l>Thou gain'ſt the name of Act ve, upright, rare,</l>
                        <l>Therefore I ceaſe to paint thy praiſes forth:</l>
                        <l>Thy ſelfe, and actions, ſhew thy reall worth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:51"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>IchCambell,</hi> Earle <hi>Lowdon,</hi> Lord high Chancelour of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Cal him real'e noble.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cal him real'e nohle,</hi> ſound his fame,</l>
                        <l>Since you do read his actions in his name.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigram.</head>
                        <l>A Hand divine. or ſome heroick quill,</l>
                        <l>Imploid with all <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> muſes skill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Muſt contribute their knowledge to contrive,</l>
                        <l>The excellence, the eminence, and ſtrive,</l>
                        <l>Yea ſtrain themſelves for to extoll thy fame,</l>
                        <l>Thy noble nature, and renowned name.</l>
                        <l>Thy worth, thy vertue, and admired wit,</l>
                        <l>Made all thy Nations wiſdom, think thee fit,</l>
                        <l>For to be choſen Chancelour Supream,</l>
                        <l>And to ſupport a Monarchs diadem.</l>
                        <l>Thy birth that burthen beſt became, but then,</l>
                        <l>Thy education did exceed all men:</l>
                        <l>As far as <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his higheſt ſphear,</l>
                        <l>Excels the ſmalleſt meteors in the aire.</l>
                        <l>Moſt famous Lord, beloved <hi>Lowdon</hi> Earle,</l>
                        <l>More beautifull then is the brighteſt pearl:</l>
                        <l>Whoſe price ſurpaſſe thoſe eſtimations high,</l>
                        <l>Within the compaſſe or Capacitie</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:52"/>Of my conceptions, ſurely I may aim</l>
                        <l>To intimate, but cannot come to them.</l>
                        <l>All <hi>Europs</hi> eies have long time gazd to ſee</l>
                        <l>Thoſe enterpriſes entertaind by thee:</l>
                        <l>And duly did determine for to ſtand,</l>
                        <l>To thoſe intentions thou didſt take in hand.</l>
                        <l>When faith fell foul, and noman muſt appear,</l>
                        <l>In none of theſe three kingdoms, thou camſt here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>And with a conſtant courage, and a mind</l>
                        <l>Moſt certain, zealous, in undaunted kind,</l>
                        <l>Thou didſt declare, with hazard of thy blood,</l>
                        <l>Thy reſolutions for Religions good.</l>
                        <l>And when confin'd by Soveraign high conſent,</l>
                        <l>Nor did thy thoughts nor alter, nor relent:</l>
                        <l>But in a pious and a prudent forme:</l>
                        <l>Paſt through the power of that tempeſtuous ſtorme:</l>
                        <l>Stood ſtedfaſt, faithfull, as that fixed Star,</l>
                        <l>Which ſtands, whereby all others ruled are.</l>
                        <l>A learned l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ght, a Peer unparaleld:</l>
                        <l>Whoſe high expreſſions in the tongues exceld,</l>
                        <l>And ſtill excels, the eloquence or skill</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Cato, Plato,</hi> or <hi>Apollo's</hi> quill:</l>
                        <l>When time ſhall ceaſe, when <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſhall not ſhine,</l>
                        <l>And human nature ſhall become divine,</l>
                        <l>When day in darkneſſe ſhall diſolve, and when</l>
                        <l>A thouſand years ſhall be the age of man:</l>
                        <l>Yea when the Spring to winter time ſhall turn:</l>
                        <l>And when the Ocean in a fire ſhall burn.</l>
                        <l>Then ſhall they ceaſe to ſing thy praiſe, and then</l>
                        <l>Thy name ſhall be quite cancelled by men.</l>
                        <l>But not till then (and that will never be)</l>
                        <l>Shall after ages ceaſe to honour thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:52"/>
                     <head>TO THE <hi>RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RABLE, Lord Major of the Citie of</hi> LONDON. WITH <hi>The Honourable Aldermen, and the reſt of the Common-councell-men.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>REnowned worthies; when I weigh your fame,</l>
                     <l>Your greatneſſe, luſtre, and your vertuous Name,</l>
                     <l>Your wiſedome, knowledge, providence, and arts,</l>
                     <l>Your grace, your goodnes, and diviner parts,</l>
                     <l>The Zeal, the love, the charities, and what</l>
                     <l>Belongs, as proper attributes to that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your power, your plenty, with your worth, and wit,</l>
                     <l>Your faith and forward arguments of it;</l>
                     <l>The higheſt honour of your enterpriſe,</l>
                     <l>Which from the ſecret of your hearts ariſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:53"/>Your noble Natures, not enough admired,</l>
                     <l>Your reall actions, active, and untyred,</l>
                     <l>Your conſtant Cariage, and unceſſant care,</l>
                     <l>The vaſt expences, daily you prepare;</l>
                     <l>Your paines and practice, in a pleaſant kinde,</l>
                     <l>Proceeding from your piety of minde:</l>
                     <l>Makes up a modell of admyred worth,</l>
                     <l>To beautifie, and ſet your glory forth,</l>
                     <l>Before whoſe feaſt, in preſence of whoſe table,</l>
                     <l>And in whoſe eyes, ſo high and honorabel,</l>
                     <l>My meane deſignes, or infants of my Muſe,</l>
                     <l>Scarce date approach; yet doubting to refuſe,</l>
                     <l>They do draw nigh; ſubmiſſively to tender<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thoſe true intentions, which I freely render,</l>
                     <l>In theſe few lines, Characters here, inſert,</l>
                     <l>As reall Emblems, of a zealous heart,</l>
                     <l>And do acknowledge I am bound to prayſe,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe who may claime, ſuch Epithets as theſe,</l>
                     <l>Grave Judges then, admit me as I am,</l>
                     <l>Though one unworthy; yet with what I came</l>
                     <l>Contemne the treaſure, not a whit for mee,</l>
                     <l>Although I bring it, yet behold, and ſee,</l>
                     <l>What I preſent, and at your vacant how'rs,</l>
                     <l>Look on his lynes, whoſe life is wholly yours.</l>
                     <l>I have contrived in a mean degree,</l>
                     <l>Though not the whole, yet an Epitomie,</l>
                     <l>Of Englands troubles, and a true relation,</l>
                     <l>Of all the ſufferings, of this famous Nation,</l>
                     <l>The cauſe was Gods, the glory is your own,</l>
                     <l>You have maintain'd the truth, and made it known,</l>
                     <l>I need not bid you perſeveer, you are,</l>
                     <l>I do perceive you, what you alwaies were,</l>
                     <l>I only throw my myte into your ſtore,</l>
                     <l>To ſhew affection not to make it more,</l>
                     <l>And do adviſe you, humbly to eſchew,</l>
                     <l>The bad diviſions, of a factious crue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:53"/>Go on with courage, as you have done ay,</l>
                     <l>It is the evening, that doth crowne the day:</l>
                     <l>Your Fame is flown' with its wings ſo far,</l>
                     <l>You do not know what things reported are,</l>
                     <l>The eyes of Europe, opened are to view,</l>
                     <l>If you continue and prove conſtant true,</l>
                     <l>Great be the Grander, wherein you may ſhine,</l>
                     <l>And heaps of honour from a hand Divine,</l>
                     <l>Be daily added in your heads, and then,</l>
                     <l>You will appeare the rareſt of all men,</l>
                     <l>This is the ſum: I have for to preſent,</l>
                     <l>Your ſervant can afford no complement,</l>
                     <l>Accept of theſe, and if you think it fit,</l>
                     <l>As you are pleaſed let me heare of it,</l>
                     <l>Your good acceptance may incourage much,</l>
                     <l>I hope your Greatnes will vouchſafe me ſuch,</l>
                     <l>So ſhall my book bear witnes at your table,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I am your Servant,</hi> Devoted as I am able.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:54"/>
                     <head>To the Renowned, Learned, and Worthy, <hi>DIVINES;</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Mr. ALEXANDER HENDERSON.</item>
                           <item>Mr. SAMUEL RUTHERFORD.</item>
                           <item>Mr. ROBERT BAYLY.</item>
                           <item>Mr. GEORGE GILESPIE.</item>
                        </list>
Commiſsioners for the CHURCH of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p rend="italic">Author. Eccho.</p>
                     <l>I Could not be reſolved of my doubt,</l>
                     <l>Nor could I finde Divinity well out:</l>
                     <l>But askt the <hi>Eccho,</hi> and it anſwer'd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> I</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Do know four Fathers of Dininity.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I cald again, if it knew where they were?</l>
                     <l>And it repli'd, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>Ile tell thee where they are.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I askt the place, or if it knew their names,</l>
                     <l>And then it ſaid, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>I know them by their ayms.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What do they aym at? Then I askt aloud,</l>
                     <l>It anſwer'd me, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>To pay what they allow'd.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What do they pay? Preach Peace to all that ſins?</l>
                     <l>Then did it anſwer, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>Pardon all that's in's.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I askt if it could name them one by one,</l>
                     <l>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And thent it anſwer'd, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>Learned Hinderſons.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I cald a ſecond, and it Eccho'd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> I</l>
                     <l>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Muſt Ecch out rare <hi>B. A. I. L. Y.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then the third, I askt it to afford,</l>
                     <l>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Eccho then did eccho <hi>Rutherford.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For one more yet, I prayd it to eſpie,</l>
                     <l>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The Ayrie Eccho whiſperd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="(Ecch.)"/> 
                        <hi>Gil es pie.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Theſe are the four profound Renownd Divines.</l>
                     <l>The Eccho ended, praiſing their Ingin's.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="apology">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:54"/>
                     <head>For Apologie to theſe Perſons of Honour.</head>
                     <l>BLame not my <hi>Muſe</hi> nor my impartiall eye,</l>
                     <l>If I miſtake your place of Heraldry;</l>
                     <l>I am not hanted with the ſame, nor yet,</l>
                     <l>Have I adviſed with your ſelves in it:</l>
                     <l>I ſeek not to engender diſcontent,</l>
                     <l>Nor meddle with your place in Parliament;</l>
                     <l>But ſee how <hi>Mars</hi> did muſter you in Warre,</l>
                     <l>As I conceive, ſo you inſerted are:</l>
                     <l>Or if I place a Member here amiſſe,</l>
                     <l>Miſconſter not my meaning here in this.</l>
                     <l>You all are Members of one body, be</l>
                     <l>Not diſunited, 'twere bad policie.</l>
                     <l>You did attend upon his Excellence</l>
                     <l>At Arms, I pray then take it in that ſence.</l>
                     <l>And if your charge did challenge you the Van;</l>
                     <l>If I miſtake it, yet be you the man.</l>
                     <l>But you remember often in the Reer,</l>
                     <l>The beſt be ranked, think it not a jeer,</l>
                     <l>Nor that I jeſt; it was more honour then</l>
                     <l>To ſtrive for place, ſo do Heroick men;</l>
                     <l>Or if I borrow for a friend, a place,</l>
                     <l>I hope you will excuſe me in this caſe.</l>
                     <l>Yea, take this New'ars gift gladly, and confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>Ye joy to ſhine ſo in your Generals <hi>Glaſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſince your honours I do ſeek with thirſt,</l>
                     <l>Let him that's firſt be laſt, and laſt be firſt.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:55"/>
                     <head>To the Right Worſhipfull and Renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Phyſitian; Doctor <hi>Alexander Ramſey.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Examen all rare ayd.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Examine all rare ayd, <hi>yet you ſhall ſtill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Rev'rence the excellencie of</hi> Ramſay's <hi>skill.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>HYpocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> got the praiſe,</l>
                        <l>The rareſt of <hi>Phiſitians</hi> in their dayes,</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Ramſay,</hi> had thoſe times produced thee,</l>
                        <l>Thou hadſt been <hi>Reckoned</hi> rareſt of the three,</l>
                        <l>They were <hi>Renown'd</hi> for <hi>Knowledge,</hi> but thy <hi>Name,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shall be more <hi>famous,</hi> far, then both of <hi>them,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>They practised moſt on <hi>ſubjects;</hi> by report,</l>
                        <l>Thy <hi>Soveraigne</hi> skill, was <hi>ſingular,</hi> at Court,</l>
                        <l>I knew no fit <hi>preferment</hi> for thy worth,</l>
                        <l>To place thee in; but I have <hi>picked</hi> thee forth,</l>
                        <l>For beſt <hi>Phiſitians;</hi> to attend on them,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe noble <hi>Preſence,</hi> may <hi>promote</hi> thy <hi>Name,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Preſerve</hi> them then, in <hi>honour ſtrength</hi> and health,</l>
                        <l>From <hi>paines</hi> diſpleaſure, and in heaps of wealth;</l>
                        <l>Which if you do, you ſhall pertake of that,</l>
                        <l>Their happie <hi>being;</hi> and your ſelfe know's what<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>But <hi>ſingular Ramſay,</hi> by thy admired skill,</l>
                        <l>Say, canſt thou cure this <hi>Epidemick</hi> ill,</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Iealouſies</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> or this ſad griefe,</l>
                        <l>The want of <hi>gold,</hi> of all diſeaſes chiefe;</l>
                        <l>Which if thou doſt, as is no doubt thou may,</l>
                        <l>(If men will but, ſubmit unto thy way)</l>
                        <l>Then we ſhall be made <hi>rich,</hi> and thou <hi>renoun'd,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt have <hi>patience</hi> ſtill: none will be ſound,</l>
                     </lg>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:55"/>
                     <head>TO <hi>MY BROTHER,</hi> Captain <hi>John Mercer.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>Hence, no more ir.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Hence, no more ire; <hi>this comes well nigh your name.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Let Anagram and actions; be the ſame.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Sonnet.</head>
                        <l>THoſe <hi>curteſies</hi> which common are to <hi>others,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>May very well be us'd between two <hi>Brothers,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>You ſee I have <hi>preſumed</hi> with my pen,</l>
                        <l>To write my minde to many <hi>worthy</hi> men.</l>
                        <l>I ſhall not therefore think it much <hi>amiſſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To viſit <hi>you</hi> with theſe few lines, in this.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Nor think's <hi>unproper,</hi> though you have the age,</l>
                        <l>For to receive, this <hi>Sonnet</hi> for a pledge</l>
                        <l>Of my <hi>reſpects;</hi> and be advis'd by me,</l>
                        <l>To let your <hi>outwards,</hi> and your <hi>minde</hi> agree.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nature,</hi> in each thing, hath <hi>perform'd,</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>In you; and <hi>Parents</hi> alſo, playd their part;</l>
                        <l>Make good theſe gifts, curb <hi>paſſion,</hi> loſe no <hi>time,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And though you think me, <hi>guilty</hi> of the <hi>crime;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which I condemn, yet ſtrive you to be better,</l>
                        <l>And for ſo doing, I ſhall be your debter.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:56"/>
                     <head>TO THE FAMOUS POET Capt. <hi>George Withers.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I go gether Verſo.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>Thy name it ſelfe ſayes; I go gether verſe.</l>
                        <l>So that thy ſtore-houſe never can be ſcarce.</l>
                        <l>The Stock Whence thou, thy lines, and loaves, do gether,</l>
                        <l>Shall freſh continue, and revive, though <hi>Wither.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Epigr.</head>
                        <l>ALL ye who brag of brave Saint <hi>George</hi> come hither,</l>
                        <l>And England, henceforth, boaſt of thy <hi>George Wither,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Lay off your emblems, do no Trophies raiſe,</l>
                        <l>Unleſſe for <hi>Withers</hi> ſolemnize no dayes,</l>
                        <l>Rare <hi>Withers,</hi> thou whoſe verſes were foretold,</l>
                        <l>As Propheſies; and ſecrets to unfold,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe young, and yet, undaunted ſpirit priz'd,</l>
                        <l>Thy rare inventions, (well nigh ſacrifiz'd)</l>
                        <l>Before thy freedome; and whoſe fluent pen,</l>
                        <l>Makes thee more famous then thoſe mighty men,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe mines of gold, and greateſt ſtore of ſuch,</l>
                        <l>Can not be reckoned, near thy worth by much,</l>
                        <l>To thee, my Muſe, though unacquainted muſt,</l>
                        <l>Into thy wing of fame; a feather thruſt,</l>
                        <l>To mount thee higher, and to make thee flye,</l>
                        <l>Above thy own expreſſions, mortals eye:</l>
                        <l>The beſt of wits, the rareſt of the Nine,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe high inventions, in thy verſe divine,</l>
                        <l>Makes me admire thee far much more, then <hi>others,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Renowned Poet; ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e and worthy <hi>Withers.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="to_the_reader">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:56"/>
                     <head>The Pen-mans Apologie to the Common Reader.</head>
                     <l>IF any take me for to be a ſtranger</l>
                     <l>That penn'd this peece, I hope there is no danger,</l>
                     <l>Or if a Native here his ſeed hath ſown,</l>
                     <l>No doubt, you will excuſe him as your own:</l>
                     <l>And if a Poet you preſume I am,</l>
                     <l>The Muſes will excuſe me whence I came,</l>
                     <l>In any thing if I have pleaſed thee,</l>
                     <l>Then I am ſure thou wilt not cenſure me:</l>
                     <l>But 'tis a thing impoſſible, that I</l>
                     <l>Can pleaſe all parties, or the ſtanders by:</l>
                     <l>'T may be thou hates ſome one of whom I write,</l>
                     <l>And therefore thou muſt rail at me in ſpight:</l>
                     <l>Or elſe thou'rt angry that I did not touch</l>
                     <l>Thy praiſes likewiſe, ſpeak of thee as much:</l>
                     <l>My free-borne Muſe, or mother of my rime,</l>
                     <l>Cannot be ti'de to humor every time:</l>
                     <l>Yet I am certain that I ſpeak to thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>If not my ſelf, my Satyre is not free:</l>
                     <l>But if thou wrongs me with an angry look;</l>
                     <l>I love not thee, more then thou loves my book.</l>
                     <l>My mind's my grand Committee, muſt not ſeek</l>
                     <l>Another Chair-man, I am charg'd to ſpeak.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:57"/>
                     <head>A Satyre.</head>
                     <l>GO ſwift wingd Satyre, fly abroad, and ſpare no earthly thing,</l>
                     <l>Thou art not to obey a law, nor ſubject to a King,</l>
                     <l>Pluck out a feather from thy quill, and fear nothing but write,</l>
                     <l>And ſee thou neither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpare thy friend, nor foe, nor men of might.</l>
                     <l>Fly in the air, where thou maiſt ſee, through clearnes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Sun,</l>
                     <l>And ceaſe not till thou cenſures all, when once thou art begun:</l>
                     <l>Tell every kind of creature who bears the ſhape of man,</l>
                     <l>That thou muſt prove impartiall, and with thy feathers fan:</l>
                     <l>Till thou wilt take the quinteſſcence of every thing thats quick,</l>
                     <l>And with a feather from thy wing wilt freely chuſe and pick:</l>
                     <l>Tell firſt the higheſt of us all, whoſe footſtool is a throne,</l>
                     <l>That Kings themſelves may catch a fall, if they be left alone:</l>
                     <l>And tell our Soveraigne, ſpare him not, but ask him, what is he</l>
                     <l>If he his Subjects once forſake? he cannot anſwer thee.</l>
                     <l>Tell tyrannizers in their teeth that they tryumph too far.</l>
                     <l>And tell the proud &amp; mighty men, they know not what they are,</l>
                     <l>Tell ſubjects, that they muſt remember they are ſubjects ſtill,</l>
                     <l>And tell the ſelf conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>d tool, thou cat'ſt not for his ill</l>
                     <l>Tell Divines that the moſt of them are diveliſh and that they</l>
                     <l>Have but a ſhew of Godlines and do not as they ſay</l>
                     <l>Tell ludges that they are unjuſt nor do they judge a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ight</l>
                     <l>And tell them that their avarice is alwaies in thy ſight</l>
                     <l>Tell Proteſtants profeſſion is almoſt dead and gone:</l>
                     <l>And tell thou knows not where to go to find Religion.</l>
                     <l>Tell that the City's full of ſchiſmes, ſects, and heriſies,</l>
                     <l>And that the hainous ſins of Sodome lurks, and in it lies:</l>
                     <l>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>k as thou marcheſt in the ſtreets, take notice, they will cry,</l>
                     <l>What do you lack? what want you Sir? what is it you will buy?</l>
                     <l>This is the Scriptures call you know<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but in another ſence,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:57"/>For thou muſt pay for every thing thou getſt, ere thou goes hence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Scripture bids thee buy for nothing, here's all things good and evil,</l>
                     <l>Thou maiſt for thy money have, and thou maiſt buy the Divel;</l>
                     <l>Go tell the bloody thirſty ſouldier, running inarreer,</l>
                     <l>And Lawyers craving whole accompts, when they come to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,</l>
                     <l>And plead for their oppreſſions, at that impartiall bar,</l>
                     <l>Arguing <hi>pro,</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> and what equivocations are:</l>
                     <l>There ſhall the trumpet ſound, and tell them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they were paid, and wood;</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Item</hi> then, and <hi>memorandum,</hi> if it be allow'd:</l>
                     <l>When all accompts ſhall be caſt up, &amp; reckonings be made even<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>By the high Committee of accompts, for the whole Kingdom of heaven:</l>
                     <l>O! then how gladly would they wiſh the moſt part of their pay</l>
                     <l>Should be abated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the reſt put to the longeſt day.</l>
                     <l>Tell when thou comes in open place, amongſt the multitude,</l>
                     <l>They are become pernicious, impertinent, and rude:</l>
                     <l>Tell Gentlemen that they are juſt like unto Apes, and that</l>
                     <l>The Courtiers are play the knaves, and ſay they know not what.</l>
                     <l>Tell trades-men they miſtake themſelves, and for their former pride,</l>
                     <l>Some have ſhut up their ſhops at home, and gone abroad to ride</l>
                     <l>Tell ſuch of them as are become Commanders for the cauſe,</l>
                     <l>They will repent them ere 'tis long, they learned ſouldiers lawes:</l>
                     <l>Tell ſuch as practice plundering, their paſtime will not laſt:</l>
                     <l>And tell the idle loyterer, 't were good that he were preſt.</l>
                     <l>Tell to the City, that their ſins, and inſolencies odd,</l>
                     <l>Have been the cauſe that many ſouls are ſacrific'd abroad,</l>
                     <l>Tell to the Preacher in the Pulpit, ſeeming ſo preciſe,</l>
                     <l>He may deceive the peoples ſight, but not his maſters eyes:</l>
                     <l>And tell the hearers of the word, ſome comes but for the faſhion:</l>
                     <l>Tell all of them, ere it be long, muſt anſwer their tranſgreſſion.</l>
                     <l>Tell husbands they are bad become, their families prophane,</l>
                     <l>And tell the females in their faces, they are wondrous vain.</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:113472:58"/>Tell every one their part, I pray thee, ſpare not high, nor low,</l>
                     <l>And tell them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thou came of purpoſe for to tell them ſo</l>
                     <l>And having flown both far and nigh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> returne, and do not fear<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But tell the errors of the time unto them that are here;</l>
                     <l>Tell in the Houſe of Parliament, but not as perſons there,</l>
                     <l>Tell them that private men may fail<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that is wondrous faire</l>
                     <l>Tell Englands <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> it fails, for all its golden caſe</l>
                     <l>And that it ſhewes not really, but counterfets the face:</l>
                     <l>Tell alſo him that made it too, what ever he pretends,</l>
                     <l>That Poets often flatter men, and have their private ends.</l>
                     <l>Thus telling all the truth abroad, returne, and do not ſtay;</l>
                     <l>For having ſpoke thy mind ſo much, thou knowes not but they may</l>
                     <l>Be ſo incens'd againſt thy ſelf, before thou art aware,</l>
                     <l>They may make bold to queſtion thee, how thou durſt fly ſo far:</l>
                     <l>For though the truth be beſt to hear, thou knowes we alwaies would,</l>
                     <l>That oftentimes you ſhould forbear, the truth muſt not be told</l>
                     <l>But thou haſt done good ſervice ſure unto the States, in this,</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt diſchargd thy conſcience too, ſo that thou canſt not miſſe</l>
                     <l>To be maintaind, and much made of; or elſe thy paines are loſt:</l>
                     <l>Thou nothing haſt, but only this, thy labour for thy coſt.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:58"/>
                     <head>To the Right Honourable, the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament: and the Right Honourable <hi>Lord Major</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> The Right worſhipfull <hi>Aldermen,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Common Councel.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The humble petition of Captain <hi>William Mercer,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who's forc'd to leave of proſe, and turn a <hi>Verſer.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                        <l>THough here I never did my ſuits preferre,</l>
                        <l>Yet I have been an old Petitioner;</l>
                        <l>And after long times wearyed fights abroad,</l>
                        <l>Am ſore tormented; with this angry rod</l>
                        <l>Of Courting, Crouching, Craving, and my eyes,</l>
                        <l>Caſt down ſo low, that I Idolatrize<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Muſt haunt Committees, follow on the Clerk,</l>
                        <l>Muſt pray, ſolicite, and make ſuch a worke,</l>
                        <l>As I have been in ſeverall Nations ſix,</l>
                        <l>But all my troubles came not nigh to vex<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Your ſupplicant, in manner like to thoſe,</l>
                        <l>As I had been one of your greateſt foes,</l>
                        <l>I have been true in ſtanding for the State</l>
                        <l>And of my friends have therefore had much hate.</l>
                        <l>I never plundred money, horſe nor arms,</l>
                        <l>Nor did the Country any kind of harms;</l>
                        <l>But took free quarter, when I had not pay,</l>
                        <l>And that was often but one meal a day:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:59"/>Would never let them kill a handſome Hen,</l>
                        <l>To feed me, if I could not pay it then,</l>
                        <l>Have borrowed from my boy, who could disburſe</l>
                        <l>Money, when I had nothing in my purſe:</l>
                        <l>Preſerv'd the People from the plundring band</l>
                        <l>Of Souldiers, and ſtill for their good did ſtand.</l>
                        <l>Yea, and with patience ſuffered for the cauſe,</l>
                        <l>According to our Covenant, and Lawes,</l>
                        <l>Not doubting, though I much run in areer,</l>
                        <l>But I ſhould ſurely have it ſome time here.</l>
                        <l>And if I were to write my finall will,</l>
                        <l>Upon my death, I never did more ill.</l>
                        <l>But now your true petitioner indeed</l>
                        <l>Is ſo confounded, as you here may read,</l>
                        <l>That I am almoſt wearied of my life,</l>
                        <l>Tir'd and tormented with this cruel ſtrife</l>
                        <l>The cries of children and an angrie woman,</l>
                        <l>Two heavy Anchors, when their ty'de unto men,</l>
                        <l>They cry for money, bread, and beer, and beefe,</l>
                        <l>But they may eat their fingers for reliefe,</l>
                        <l>Then call they Father; What have we to burne?</l>
                        <l>Poor children thinks that I can do their turne.</l>
                        <l>How doth your ſelves content theſe Infant cares?</l>
                        <l>Or do you bid them go and ſay their Prayers?</l>
                        <l>Perchance ye do, and't may be ſo do I,</l>
                        <l>But then they enter in a lachry my,</l>
                        <l>And tels me this, what have we now to eat?</l>
                        <l>The grace is ſaid, but we can get no meat,</l>
                        <l>My creditors have cal'd ſo oft unto me</l>
                        <l>That now they ſweare they ſhortly will undoe me.</l>
                        <l>They ſay my charge hath turn'd me in a cheat,</l>
                        <l>And ſuch like things have hapned me of late</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:59"/>When I'me abroad, I ſtand and ſtare to skan,</l>
                        <l>Leſt I on ſudden meet a Marſhalls man:</l>
                        <l>This is moſt grievous, and a great diſgrace,</l>
                        <l>A Souldier dare not look men in the face:</l>
                        <l>And I'me already run ſo in the ſcore</l>
                        <l>To tell the truth, they will not truſt me more.</l>
                        <l>And now the Printer, and the Stationer,</l>
                        <l>Threatens to priſon your Petitioner.</l>
                        <l>For I who could before theſe Wars did enter,</l>
                        <l>Attaine more truſt upon one lines debenter,</l>
                        <l>Then now I can for either word or writ,</l>
                        <l>They do not care for both, here is the ſpite:</l>
                        <l>And if I tell them much to me is <note n="*" place="margin">900. l.</note> ow'd,</l>
                        <l>Then ſay they; <hi>Item, if it be alow'd.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Nor can I walk along the ſtreet, and look</l>
                        <l>Vpon a Butcher, nor come nigh a Cook</l>
                        <l>But they ſtep in, between me and their ſtall,</l>
                        <l>And there they ſtand, till I be in the Hall,</l>
                        <l>Still as I paſſe, I hear them whiſpering, So,</l>
                        <l>And ſends a boy to dog me where I go;</l>
                        <l>They are afraid leſt hungry men prove raſh</l>
                        <l>And ſeize upon their unprepared fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſh.</l>
                        <l>This is my caſe, but this doth me recheriſh,</l>
                        <l>So many worthies will not let me periſh,</l>
                        <l>Nor lay my lines aſide, (it is not that)</l>
                        <l>Unleſſe contented, which is aimed at.</l>
                        <l>Nigh four years now I have been in this war,</l>
                        <l>Yet I am poorer then I was, by far,</l>
                        <l>And all this time, a Captain too, to Horſe,</l>
                        <l>But my eſtate ſtill waxed worſe and worſe.</l>
                        <l>How could I chooſe, you ſee what was my pay,</l>
                        <l>And what I took, you likewiſe heare me ſay:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:60"/>In two years time I had not pay almoſt</l>
                        <l>For once a day to buy a buttered toaſt.</l>
                        <l>I loſt my being in that <hi>Iriſh</hi> land,</l>
                        <l>Where by commiſſion I had firſt Command.</l>
                        <l>My Fathers heir was therein put to Sword,</l>
                        <l>His wife was alſo cruely devour'd,</l>
                        <l>His goods deſtroy'd, his Children ſent abroad</l>
                        <l>To beg; and I was ſcourged with this rod.</l>
                        <l>Yet not the leſſe, if proſe nor verſe prevails,</l>
                        <l>There's no more hope, I muſt ly by the heeles:</l>
                        <l>Nor dare I ſpeak, or if, this is my lot,</l>
                        <l>They ſhake their heads, and ſay, you are a Scot,</l>
                        <l>Deriding me, as if I were forlorne;</l>
                        <l>Or to be cald a <hi>Scots man</hi> were a ſcorn,</l>
                        <l>The caſe is alter'd, for when I came here</l>
                        <l>The <hi>Scots</hi> were counted Loving brethren deare:</l>
                        <l>Nor's that the love the Scripture doth commend,</l>
                        <l>Whom Chriſt did love, he lov'd unto the end.</l>
                        <l>But good my Lords, and noble Gentlemen</l>
                        <l>Be pleaſ'd to heare, and have but patience then,</l>
                        <l>Yea, pardon me, who is ſo forc'd to preſſe</l>
                        <l>Vpon your patience, I can do no leſſe:</l>
                        <l>Nor let the ſpleen of any one or two</l>
                        <l>If there be ſuch; ſtop what you mind to doe,</l>
                        <l>The beſt amongſt you, have ſome private foe,</l>
                        <l>And ſo may I, for any thing I know.</l>
                        <l>Vertue's alwaies envide, there's none ſo witty</l>
                        <l>To ſhun the ſlandrous tongues, the more's the pitty.</l>
                        <l>But let them ſpeak and prove, which if they do,</l>
                        <l>I'le burne my bookes, and will be baniſht too.</l>
                        <l>The Parliament for freedome needs not ſit,</l>
                        <l>If one will do all that's requir'd in it:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:60"/>And if that Juſtice may not claim its place</l>
                        <l>Where malice ſits, that were a fearfull caſe.</l>
                        <l>I'le take my oath, (all times I were abroad)</l>
                        <l>And prove it too, though ye may think it odd:</l>
                        <l>I never went into a Tavern twice</l>
                        <l>Nor in an Ale-houſe was I ever thrice</l>
                        <l>To call for drink: nor drunken in my time,</l>
                        <l>There's no man can accuſe me of that crime:</l>
                        <l>Nor do I know, (pray think it not a tale)</l>
                        <l>The prizes of the Wines, nor beer, nor ale:</l>
                        <l>So, never drinking for to make me raſh,</l>
                        <l>I'me ſure I ſeldom faulted being freſh.</l>
                        <l>I ſcorn'd to plunder, cal'd it baſe to rob,</l>
                        <l>Reſolved rather to be juſt like <hi>Iob,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Both poor and upright, but I ſee what falls</l>
                        <l>In favours of ſuch curſed Animals</l>
                        <l>As plaug'd the people, Fortune ſmiles on them,</l>
                        <l>They riſe to honours, and they have no blame.</l>
                        <l>But this may be, that ſaying to fulfill</l>
                        <l>Which is, <hi>The wicked flouriſh in their ill,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>I have more comfort of my honeſt mind,</l>
                        <l>Though for a time I oppoſition find,</l>
                        <l>Then they who gain their riches ſo with ſorrow,</l>
                        <l>And may be proud to day, but poor to morrow.</l>
                        <l>My heart ſhall hold my reſolution ſtill,</l>
                        <l>Endure with patience, if I do no ill,</l>
                        <l>I have perform'd that part to me belongs,</l>
                        <l>And God ſhall be a witneſſe of my wrongs,</l>
                        <l>If I muſt periſh, but I do appeal</l>
                        <l>Vnto your honours, hops for to prevaile</l>
                        <l>In this my ſuit ſo honeſt, juſt and true,</l>
                        <l>But do ſubmit me, wholy unto you,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:61"/>Whoſe greatneſſe will grant pardon to my ſin,</l>
                        <l>For being ſo preſumptuous herein,</l>
                        <l>How can I chooſe? For after three yeers war</l>
                        <l>I find them ſtriving fully to debarr</l>
                        <l>Me of my pay, which truly I deſerve,</l>
                        <l>The only way me to conſtrain to ſtrave,</l>
                        <l>Or beg my bread, as others dayly do:</l>
                        <l>But more then this I'le tell thee ſomething too:</l>
                        <l>At ſix moneths end, when I my 'compts deſir'd,</l>
                        <l>To go to <hi>Cornhill</hi> then I was requir'd,</l>
                        <l>To that Committee, which of Lawyers be,</l>
                        <l>Be what they will, they were too hard for me:</l>
                        <l>For though my debts I did preſent moſt true,</l>
                        <l>Yet they write <hi>Item, if the ſame be due:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which when I ſaw, I vex'd, and waxed wroth,</l>
                        <l>And then they told me, they were on their oath:</l>
                        <l>For what? ſaid I; they anſwer'd, to do right,</l>
                        <l>Or as it ſhould ſeem good in their own ſight:</l>
                        <l>Well, this they did, but when we came to read,</l>
                        <l>We found it needfull they would come to plead</l>
                        <l>At that Committee; where they did returne us</l>
                        <l>Who when we came with our accompts, did ſcorne us:</l>
                        <l>This griev'd my ſoule, to run ſo up and down</l>
                        <l>From him, to him, and thorow ſo long a Town</l>
                        <l>As this, and yet when all is come to all</l>
                        <l>I cannot get a penny, though I call</l>
                        <l>My very eyes out of my dolefull head,</l>
                        <l>Al's noe to them, for they will make no ſpeed.</l>
                        <l>They ſend me there to heare the monie Chink</l>
                        <l>In <hi>Lumberſtreet,</hi> no queſtion ſome men think</l>
                        <l>That that will tempt me, then they will pretend</l>
                        <l>If I ſhould rob men, I'me for my own end.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:61"/>Then think not ſtrange although my verſe be bad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>For ſuch like things, have made me almoſt mad.</l>
                        <l>I borrowed oft to pay my men abroad,</l>
                        <l>And not to pay me that, were very odd:</l>
                        <l>My poor half <note n="*" place="margin">400. l.</note> part, out of the publick purſe,</l>
                        <l>Or leſſe then that, would free me from this curſe,</l>
                        <l>I do not crave you in ſo high a meaſure</l>
                        <l>So ſmall a ſum would not exhauſt your treaſure.</l>
                        <l>What comes of all Collections and exciſe?</l>
                        <l>Malignants monie? Flies it in the skies?</l>
                        <l>Pray if ye will not pay me, make me then</l>
                        <l>But one full fortnight a Committee-man,</l>
                        <l>I'e pay my ſelfe; nor will I charge the State,</l>
                        <l>But only take the mony I can get:</l>
                        <l>If I would ask a Groat, you would not grant</l>
                        <l>It think, although ye ſaw me ſtrave for want<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ten thouſand pounds to call for or a penny</l>
                        <l>Is all alike, ye cannot part with any.</l>
                        <l>To give me nothing were a bad revenge,</l>
                        <l>And for my pains to let me ſtarve were ſtrange:</l>
                        <l>It makes me think the thing is true they ſay,</l>
                        <l>Ye are reſolved never for to pay:</l>
                        <l>But that were ſtrange, would make me wonder too,</l>
                        <l>Since for the truth ye make ſo much adoe:</l>
                        <l>but therein act as you ſhall think it beſt,</l>
                        <l>Give me my pay; I ſtrive not for the reſt:</l>
                        <l>There's not a man will do ſo much as ſpeek</l>
                        <l>Or look, without allowance every week:</l>
                        <l>Yet I did fight, Faſt, watch, had much to do</l>
                        <l>To ſave my life, and muſt have nothing too.</l>
                        <l>Malignants ſees me in ſo poor a plight,</l>
                        <l>They laugh, ond tellsme I am ſerved right:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:62"/>Nor hate they me becauſe that it is I,</l>
                        <l>But I will tell the reaſon by and by,</l>
                        <l>They do abhor all of that Northern Nation</l>
                        <l>Who joynes not with them in their Congregation:</l>
                        <l>For though they did make promiſe thereunto,</l>
                        <l>It was when they had greater things to do:</l>
                        <l>Like people in a ſtrait, but now they'r free,</l>
                        <l>The turns nigh done, they care no more for me.</l>
                        <l>'Tis not our part upon their ſouls to preſſe,</l>
                        <l>And for my part I freely muſt confeſſe:</l>
                        <l>If they will pay me I will ſpeak and plead</l>
                        <l>Againſt my Country men to go with ſpeed.</l>
                        <l>And let them preach, and uſe their minds to pray,</l>
                        <l>Or do ev'n what they pleaſe to do or ſay,</l>
                        <l>Or where or how, yea be they wives or men,</l>
                        <l>And ſo I think they would be pleaſed then:</l>
                        <l>For can I force them, where they will not do?</l>
                        <l>Time is not yet for lew and Gentile too.</l>
                        <l>I hold me bound of Conſcience for to move them,</l>
                        <l>But I muſt neither challenge nor reprove them.</l>
                        <l>Preach in their ſtreets or in their private Hall,</l>
                        <l>(If not in Church) by my conſent they ſhall.</l>
                        <l>Nor ſay I'me wanton, though I write in verſe,</l>
                        <l>I had not done ſo, had I not been ſcarce</l>
                        <l>Of mony, Lodging, credit, and the reſt:</l>
                        <l>Nor could I well conſider what was beſt</l>
                        <l>To do; for I had ſpent ſo long a time</l>
                        <l>I proſe, that I was forc'd to write in rime,</l>
                        <l>Reſolving what in me did ly, to do,</l>
                        <l>And if I periſh, lay the fault on you.</l>
                        <l>I was made come, and go, and come again,</l>
                        <l>But all I did was labour ſpent in vain:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:62"/>From one to tother, to that Committee man,</l>
                        <l>And then as wiſe as when I firſt began.</l>
                        <l>Some ſaid I'le do't, then ſaid I am but one,</l>
                        <l>And then they ſaid ye muſt petition:</l>
                        <l>They bid me faſt and pray, if I bee ſick,</l>
                        <l>When I have well nigh faſted all the weeke,</l>
                        <l>And if I tell them that my ſpirit's ſpent,</l>
                        <l>They bid me then, be patient, and content,</l>
                        <l>The Colonels have laid their cloaths in paund,</l>
                        <l>And many Majors have not ſtrength to ſtand,</l>
                        <l>The Captains and Commanders all in chiefe</l>
                        <l>Are quite confounded, even with very griefe,</l>
                        <l>And many good men faſt a moneth from meate,</l>
                        <l>And when they have it, then they cannot eat;</l>
                        <l>Now tell them this, and zealous like they pauſe,</l>
                        <l>And ſayes, that we muſt ſuffer for the cauſe:</l>
                        <l>Thoſe Characters <hi>Jobs</hi> meſſengers may ſpell,</l>
                        <l>For I alone, am only left to tell:</l>
                        <l>Is this the dealing with a friend or brother?</l>
                        <l>Or mutuall manner of maintaining other?</l>
                        <l>Yet if I muſt go, furniſht as I came,</l>
                        <l>I cannot be made worſer then I am,</l>
                        <l>Nor is this halfe the burthen that I beare,</l>
                        <l>No fleſh, and blood would ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r nor endure</l>
                        <l>Thoſe great neglects, wherewith I am ſuppreſt,</l>
                        <l>So that I am aſhamed to confes't;</l>
                        <l>But if it were not for the reverence,</l>
                        <l>(A matter of ſo mighty conſequence,)</l>
                        <l>Which I do bear this hopefull Parliament,</l>
                        <l>And that I likewiſe look for ſome content,</l>
                        <l>I would cry out, though I therefore ſhould dy,</l>
                        <l>And let the World even know my deſtiny.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:63"/>Thus craving leave to ſpeak, pleaſe you to read,</l>
                        <l>This is the Subjects freedom which I plead,</l>
                        <l>As for the iſſue, I preſcribe not what,</l>
                        <l>The honour of the houſe will think on that.</l>
                        <l>But I beleve your greatneſſe will conſider</l>
                        <l>To make my State, as firſt when I cam hither,</l>
                        <l>So wreſtling with you, till I have my will</l>
                        <l>Then will I think it time for to be ſtill:</l>
                        <l>You know that <hi>Iacob,</hi> by his faith abode,</l>
                        <l>Nor would he leave off wreſtling with his God</l>
                        <l>Till he obtain'd; ſo you ſtill with your King</l>
                        <l>Have wreſtled likewiſe, till ye have the thing.</l>
                        <l>Even ſo the woman in the Goſpel got</l>
                        <l>What ſhe deſir'd, yea ſhe departed not</l>
                        <l>Till ſhe obtain'd; and Jacob on demand</l>
                        <l>Obtain'd the bleſſing, at good <hi>Iſaacks</hi> hand.</l>
                        <l>What ſhall I ſay? Is not one <hi>Iſaack</hi> then</l>
                        <l>Amongſt ſo many full five hundred men?</l>
                        <l>Or if ther be: in vain bear not the name,</l>
                        <l>Let me receive the bleſſing then from them.</l>
                        <l>For I'me affraid leſt <hi>Eſau</hi> like I ſell</l>
                        <l>My whole debenter for a diſh of Kell,</l>
                        <l>Therefore I do determine ſtill to call,</l>
                        <l>Till I have ſome part, I deſire not all.</l>
                        <l>I hate to beg, but being ſo orethrown</l>
                        <l>I humbly hope ye'l help me to mine own.</l>
                        <l>I have petition'd, and I do not doubt</l>
                        <l>before the queſtion is reſolv'd about.</l>
                        <l>Amongſt thoſe worthies whom I do implore,</l>
                        <l>But they will take a courſe to cure my ſore:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:113472:63"/>For if I had but third part of my pay</l>
                        <l>To free my charges, I would go my way.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>I have no more to ſay,</l>
                        <l>but I ſhall ever pray.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <div type="anagram">
                        <head>William Mercer.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Anagr. I am very ill cu'r me.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Iam very ill cu'r me</hi> of my Paine,</l>
                           <l>Or elſe my wars and verſes are in vain.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I am veri ill cu'r me,</hi> if I die</l>
                           <l>Of this diſeaſe ye'l ſpoil my Poetry.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I am veri ill cu'r me,</hi> but if not,</l>
                           <l>I never will write more while I'me a <hi>Scot.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I am veri ill cu'r me,</hi> if ſo long,</l>
                           <l>My muſe may chuſe to ſing another ſong.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:64"/>
                     <head>One word more to <hi>Momus.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <l>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e wide mouthd <hi>Momus</hi> rage and rail thy fill</l>
                     <l>Spue out thy venom words can do no ill,</l>
                     <l>But to thy ſelf, thy being is thereby,</l>
                     <l>For having ſpent thy ſpirits, thou muſt die.</l>
                     <l>The crawling ſnail the paſſenger to ſcorne,</l>
                     <l>Cannot forbear, extols his feeble horne,</l>
                     <l>But trod upon, he quickly doth withdraw,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he knowes his weapons have no awe;</l>
                     <l>Pluck in thy horne, ſpue out thy venom then,</l>
                     <l>Thou Miſcreant, vile creature of men.</l>
                     <l>This is the worſt I wiſh to ſuch a ſnail,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſlandrous tongue were ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>king in thy—</l>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:64"/>
                     <head>To the ſcornfull Paſſenger.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>SLight not my lines, nor lay my labours by,</l>
                        <l>Laugh not to ſcorn, becauſe the Author's I:</l>
                        <l>I know thou'ſt come, and with diſdainfull look,</l>
                        <l>Wilt, paſſing by, ſay, what's this <hi>Mercers</hi> book?</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But <hi>Mercers</hi> book, if thou couldſt take the time,</l>
                        <l>Or ſtay from Taverns, to peruſe his rime:</l>
                        <l>Will pay thee home, preſuming to appear,</l>
                        <l>Or lay thy hands upon theſe Perſons here.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Without thou ſtand bareheaded, and a farre,</l>
                        <l>Such one as thou ſhouldſt not come wherethey are.</l>
                        <l>Forbear therefore, in ſilence, ſtand aſide,</l>
                        <l>Or take not notice, <hi>Mercer</hi> makes a pride<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>If he approach, and ſples ſuch in the place,</l>
                        <l>To look amiſſe: he ſpits into their face.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:65"/>
                     <head>Ad Eundem.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>MY Chriſtall glaſſe, clear, ſpotleſse, clean, and pure,</l>
                        <l>Can no infectious filt by breath indure,</l>
                        <l>To blow upon't ſo alſo would my Muſe</l>
                        <l>Be even as raſh, if ſhe knew how to chuſe:</l>
                        <l>But ſhe is mine, and cares not for the frown</l>
                        <l>Of any churliſh, baſe, backbiting clowne,</l>
                        <l>As for my glaſſe, in innocence it ſtands,</l>
                        <l>If ſtaind by thee, between a knaves two hands.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>William Mercer, Anagr.</head>
                        <l>I am merrili cru'l,</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <head>Verſ.</head>
                        <l>I am merrili cru'l to <hi>Momus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>For I wiſh all ſuch fellowes were from us.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>From my Lodging in</hi> King-ſtreet Weſtminſter, <hi>at the three</hi> Pidgeons. <date>Ian. 6. <hi>1645.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="poem">
                     <pb facs="tcp:113472:65"/>
                     <head>Vpon the title of the Book.</head>
                     <l>THere are ſome books which bears the very Name</l>
                     <l>That mine does own, yet they are not the ſame,</l>
                     <l>Thou never heldſt a glaſſe before thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>VVherein thou ſaw all theſe Nobilities,</l>
                     <l>And worthies, wherefore thou muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſse,</l>
                     <l>'Tis fitly named <hi>Englands Looking-glaſſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or if this <hi>glaſſe</hi> ſhould have been calld by me,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>glaſſe</hi> of theſe three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> 'twere no lye.</l>
                     <l>Then with a threefold reverence ſee thou ſtand</l>
                     <l>And looking in it, hold thy hat in hand.</l>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>VV. M.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
